<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Theologia Germanica. Or, Mysticall divinitie : a little golden manuall briefly discovering the mysteries, sublimity, perfection and simplicity of Christianity, in belief and practise. Written above 250 years since in high Dutch, &amp; for its worth translated into Latine, and printed at Antwarp, 1558. Whereto is added definitions theologicall and philosophicall. Also a treatise of the soul, and other additions not before printed.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 232 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 99 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95692</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T858</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1162_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210095</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868924</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868924</idno>
            <idno type="VID">121281</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95692)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 121281)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 251:E1162[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Theologia Germanica. Or, Mysticall divinitie : a little golden manuall briefly discovering the mysteries, sublimity, perfection and simplicity of Christianity, in belief and practise. Written above 250 years since in high Dutch, &amp; for its worth translated into Latine, and printed at Antwarp, 1558. Whereto is added definitions theologicall and philosophicall. Also a treatise of the soul, and other additions not before printed.</title>
                  <author>Randall, Giles, translator.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 176, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Sweeting, at the Angell in Popes head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, by Giles Randall, of the Latin translation of the original High Dutch.</note>
                  <note>Preface signed: Giles Randall.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "October [the] 24th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>God --  Worship and love --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Mystical union --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:121281:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Theologia Germanica.</hi> Or, Myſticall DIVINITIE: A Little Golden MANUALL briefly Diſcovering the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, ſublimity, perfection and ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of Chriſtianity, in Belief and Practiſe.</p>
            <p>Written above 250 years ſince in high Dutch, &amp; for its worth tranſlated into La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, and printed at <hi>Antwarp,</hi> 1558.</p>
            <p>Whereto is added Definitions Theologicall and Philoſophicall.</p>
            <p>Alſo a <hi>Treatiſe of the Soul,</hi> and other Additions not before Printed.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Tim. 3.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And without controverſie, great is the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of godlineſſe.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>John Sweeting,</hi> at the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell</hi> in <hi>Popes head</hi> Alley. 1648.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:121281:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:121281:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHoſoever thou art that loveſt and rejoyceſt in the ſublimity, and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of truth; I have here preſented thee with a Manual, entituled, <hi>The German Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinitie;</hi> a Book firſt written by a certain godly Prieſt, of the Order of the Lords of <hi>Teutonici,</hi> in high <hi>Dutch;</hi> about two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and fifty years ſince, and afterward, for the incomparable value thereof it was tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated out of the <hi>Dutch</hi> into the <hi>Latine</hi> tongue; by <hi>John Theophilus,</hi> and printed at <hi>Antwerpe</hi> 1558; in which tongue it did lye a long ſeaſon veiled and obſcured, from the eye of the illiterate and unexpert in the ſame: untill, ſome years ſince, through the deſires and induſtries of ſome of our own Countrimen, lovers of the Truth, it was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain tranſlated, and made to ſpeak to thee in thine own Dialect and Language. But the time of its Nativity being under the late,
<pb facs="tcp:121281:3"/>wiſe, and wary Hierarchie, who had mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polized and engroſſed the diſcovery of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers into their own hands, keeping the people, wiſely, at a diſtance, and dealing out to them, what, and ſo much only, for quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity and quality, as ſeemed beſt to their grave wiſdoms and diſcretions; leſt they ſhould grow as wiſe, if not wiſer then their Teachers; and ſo the rude vulgar ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as one of us: it walked up and down this City in Manuſcripts at deer rates, from hand to hand, of ſome well-willets to truth, in clandeſtine, and private manner; like <hi>Moſes</hi> in his Arke, or the little Child fled and hid from <hi>Herod:</hi> never daring to croud into the Preſſe, fearing the ruffe uſage of thoſe then in authoritie; whoſe maxime it was, <hi>That the Prieſts lips ſhould preſerve knowledge,</hi> though miſunderſtood, or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed at leaſt: forgetting this Prieſt to be the high Prieſt Jeſus Chriſt after the order of <hi>Melchiſedeck.</hi> But now it hath obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſuch auſpicious favour, as to appear without bluſh in the moſt publique way; it being uſhered into the world under the ſafe conduct of an <hi>Imprimatur,</hi> a worthy work of piety and charity, the firſt to the truth it ſelf, that it might not be buried in
<pb facs="tcp:121281:3"/>ſilence through unknown tongues, the other to our own Countrymen, that they might not be buried in ignorance; and that the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous lights or lamps kindled in other Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, might not be rendred uſeleſſe, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable to the meaneſt in literature.</p>
            <p>The Author, Tranſlators, and Licencer have done their parts, what remaineth now? but thine to be performed, which is, delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately to read, ſeriouſly to weigh, ſpiritually to diſcern, and piouſly to uſe and reduce in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to practice and life, what thou ſhalt finde worthy herein: proving all things, and hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding faſt that which is good.</p>
            <p>The Tranſlator <hi>John Theophilus,</hi> in his Preface hereunto affixed, hath ſaved me the labour of informing thee, touching the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour, Nature, Matter, Method, and Style thereof, and in the Table annexed, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned in the end hereof wil direct thee to the ſeveral Chapters, and their pages, wich their diſtinct Contents.</p>
            <p>There is nothing left behind for me do, neither to it, or thee; but only to invite thee to taſte and ſee how ſweet, how full of life and marrow this ſmall Tracta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e is. it is as the extract or quinteſſence of other more thick and darkly compoſed Treatiſes of
<pb facs="tcp:121281:4"/>Theology; being much in little: thou ſhalt finde ſome kernels herein with their ſhell ready broken to thine hand; ſome Riddles in their plain ſence unridled; ſome myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Hiſtories revealed: ſo, that in many things the Scripture Parables are ſo explai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that thou ſhalt ſay, through the light of the truth herein; now know<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we that thou ſpeakeſt plainly and not in parables; myſteries hidden from former ages, being now in meaſure more brought to light. The Authors minde in the <hi>Latine</hi> dreſſe was elegantly, ſignificantly and perſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly expreſſed; it may be the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſtyle will not be ſo taking; yet if matter rather than words, be it thou ſeekeſt, here thou haſt it according to the beſt ſufficiencie of the Tranſlatour, as I ſuppoſe; though he be to me altogether unknown.</p>
            <p>In fine, it may well be called the <hi>German</hi> Divinitie, the child is like the Father, it ſheweth it ſelf one of that Imperiall Race, which beareth the Spread Eagle for its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe. For as the Eagle in flight is higheſt, ſwifteſt, in ſight cleereſt, in fight ſtrongeſt; ſo this Tractate ſoareth aloft, buildeth on high, even above the ſtarry Heavens, bearing her chickins the children of Truth, upon
<pb facs="tcp:121281:4"/>wing to the face of the Sun, ſpeedeth unto the fartheſt end of truth, pierceth into the inwards and bowels thereof, and over-pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the mind with her veritie, chaſing away deceitfull vanity. Were it's worth but known, there would neither want hand or heart to give it entertainment: what more ſhall I ſay ? but as the Apoſtle in another caſe, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe hoſpitality, for thereby ſome have entertained Angels;</hi> ſo uſe thou hoſpita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to this <hi>German</hi> ſtranger, who knows but that, although he cometh to thee in the evening and twi-light of thy underſtanding, ſo that at, and ſometime after it's firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, 't appear to thee as the Angels did, but mean and in mans garbe, yet at the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe before it depart from thee thou mayſt ſee the Spirit and Angel of Gods Truth in it: and if the Father of Lights and Spirits ſhal lead thee profitably into and through this, it ſhal be an engagement to him, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent thee with ſome other of the like nature, who is a lover of thee and the truth in the Truth.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Giles Randall.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:121281:5"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE OF JOHN THEOPHILUS, Who tranſlated it out of high Dutch into Latine.</head>
            <p>THis little Book hath ſo much delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me, that I thought fit to tranſlate it into Latine; the ſtile is ſhort and pithy, which may be compared to a green grove; although little, yet ſo planted, that therein is no Tree ſet only for pleaſure and not for fruit, but is every where full of fruit-bearing ſtocks: Even ſo this little book doth not delight the Reader with any elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of phraſe, with no painting intice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or (as it were) flowers of ſpeech; but it doth deliver meer precepts, and thoſe moſt profitable and behoveful to the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of a Chriſtian: Indeed in regard of
<pb facs="tcp:121281:5"/>the ſhortneſs it is ſomewhat obſcure, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to be read over, and that with diligence.</p>
            <p>Alſo I add further, that if any man be deſirous to read this Book, to the end only to increaſe his knowledg, and not to do the things contained therin, he reads it in vain; for he that intends to become a skilful huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman, muſt put his hand to the plough.</p>
            <p>As concerning my tranſlation, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that I have neither added nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted any thing from the Author, and I could no more avoyd obſcurity in tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a book compiled with much affected brevity, then the Author himſelf in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of it; yet I counſel the Reader that he would often and attentively read it, which may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ve in ſtead of a Comment; I have uſed ſome words in it, as theſe; <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goity, Selfneſs, Meity, Deified, Diſpoſence, Perſonal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ity, &amp;c.</hi> neceſſity compelling me thereunto, becauſe the Author uſeth that manner of ſpeech; wherein I ought to be thought no more blameable then Tidley, who doubted not to be bold in uſing the words <hi>Appiety and Lentallity;</hi> A Writer may make bold (when neceſſity requireth it) to command words, and not to learn them</p>
            <p>The Inſcription of this Book is, <hi>Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia
<pb facs="tcp:121281:6"/>Germanica,</hi> the Author is not named, only I find it written in a certain little Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to the Book, that he was one of thoſe who are called <hi>Dun Teutonici,</hi> or Dutch Lords, the French call them Knights of the <hi>Rhodes,</hi> and that he was a Prieſt and Governor in the houſe of <hi>Teutonici,</hi> or high Dutch at <hi>Frankfort.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Argument is of the new man, or the new creature, for he ſheweth the manner how a man may be reſtored, and return to God, from whence he is faln by following his own will; It is neceſſary that he bewilling to be reſtored, becauſe medicines are to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their diſeaſes, that he be deprived of his own will &amp; follow the will of God; and no man can ſerve two masters; but as a man may very well put out his own eyes, or kill himſelf, yet cannot reſtore himſelf to ſight or life again: even ſo man is in <hi>Adam</hi> prone to deſtroy himſelf and all his poſterity by following his own will. But neither he, nor any who is guilty, and overthrown by his ſin, can poſſibly ſave himſelf, or repair the breach: It was neceſſary again, for the ſaving of the world, that one ſhould ariſe and exist who was holy, harmleſs and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled, ſeparate from ſinners, to deliver o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb facs="tcp:121281:6"/>from ſin, and teach the way of life, and this was Jeſus Chriſt the Son of the living God, to whom all power is given both in heaven and earth, who doth not only teach man this way to ſalvation, but alſo giveth them power by Faith to walk in it.</p>
            <p>I would not hereby have you understand a dead Faith, for that is no more Faith then a dead man is a man; but a working and living Faith, ſuch a one as Saint <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> deſcribeth, together with the works and effects thereof, ſaying, <hi>Add to your faith vertue, and to your vertue knowledg, and to your knowledg temperance, and to tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance patience, and to patience godlineſs, and to godlineſs brotherly kindneſs, and to brotherly kindneſs charity. For if theſe things remain and abound in you, they will make you that you ſhall neither be barren nor unfruitful in the knowledg of our Lord Jeſus. But he that lacketh theſe things is blind, and cannot ſee afar off, and hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten that he was purged from his old ſins: Wherefore the rather, brethren, give all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence to make your calling and election ſure; for if theſe things be in you, you ſhall never fail.</hi> S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks of a true and live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly faith, which doth not only procure unto a
<pb facs="tcp:121281:7"/>man the forgiveneſs of his ſins by the merit of Chriſt, but alſo effecteth, that as before be yeelded his members as weapons of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs unto ſin, ſo hereafter he may give them as inſtruments of righteouſnes to do well. And becauſe S. <hi>Peter</hi> in this place doth deſcribe a certain ladder to ſalvation, I purpoſe to make it plain, whereby we may more evidently perceive by which ſteps we may aſcend to the top thereof, leſt that any man ſhould be content to ſtand only upon the firſt ſtep, and yet think he had attained to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalvation from which he was diſtant many degrees. Therefore (according to S. <hi>Peter</hi>) faith bringeth forth vertue, that is, ſtrength and ability to perform thoſe things which thou beleeveſt are to be done as ſo taught from God; As for example, Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands us to love our enemies, and to do good to them which do evil to us: Now there are ſome who beleeve that this can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be done, again they hate their enemies and do them all miſchief: others beleeve that it is to be done by the aſſiſtance of God, and therefore do good to their enemies. Conſider all ſects and kinds of men, and you ſhall find, that thoſe, who beleeve it is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to be done, do act the ſame; and that
<pb facs="tcp:121281:7"/>Chriſt, who hath given them power to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, hath given them power alſo to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form his Commandments; for it is not ſaid in vain; that all things are poſſible to him that beleeveth: And this I ſay generally of all other precepts of Chriſt, <hi>As thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeveſt</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>ſo be it to thee:</hi> this is generally to be taken, look how much faith any one hath; and ſo much ſtrength of vertue he hath alſo. And vertue beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth knowledge, for true knowledg conſiſts in experience, which comes to paſs when a man is made able to perform ſomething, doth certainly know that that which before he did beleeve, he did not certainly know might have been performed: Examples hereof we have in <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Joſhua,</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> who did overcome the <hi>Canaanites<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> for then did they certainly know that thoſe might be overcome, as they had before beleeved: but the reſt of the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites,</hi> who did not beleeve that this could be done, could not do it: and again, they knew it not: So at this day ſuch as do not beleeve that ſuch a the power of Chriſt as that he is able to beat down the power of the Serpent under the feet of the faithful, thoſe men are not able to reſiſt ſin, therefore they
<pb facs="tcp:121281:8"/>know not how it may be done, and therefore deny it; but thoſe who beleeve, can do it by faith, and know certainly that it may be done, and again affirm it to be true.</p>
            <p>Knowledg bringeth forth temperance, for a man confirmed with this knowledg, goeth forward to the mark, hoping for the ſame ſucceſs in the reſt: and therefore with-holds himſelf from bodily luſts and pleaſures which fight againſt the ſoul, leſt being hindred by them he be deprived of his Crown of victory. Now as the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> did vex and perſecute <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> when it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled againſt them, having before of its own accord ſerved and obeyed them: In like manner it falleth out in all rebellions of Subjects; for the luſts and pleaſures which before we voluntarily ſerved, when we rebel againſt them by temperance, do vex us in renewing their deſires, and breed us grief as much as before they did delight; which that we may bear manfully, we ſtand in need of patience: And becauſe we know that this trouble which we muſt undergo, in reſiſting theſe wicked luſts and affections in bearing of injuries, doth far exceed our ſtrength, let us earneſtly call upon God with <hi>David,</hi> that be would teach and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh
<pb facs="tcp:121281:8"/>our hands in the battel, and that he would give us ſtrength for the victory, which invocation and truſt in him is true godlineſs. Further, having obtained benefits of God by this devotion, we do love him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain for theſe benefits, and we deſire to give him thanks: for even by nature it is ordain'd that thou canſt not but love him who out of his love hath done thee good; but becauſe we can give him nothing (for he needs not our goods) ſeeing all things are his, we turn our love upon them whom he loves and commendeth unto us, that is to ſay, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on godly men, and out of love we do them good. And becauſe this love, which we bear to God and our brethren, in regard of Gods benefits beſtowed upon us, is imperfect, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing joyned with the love of our ſelves, that is, of our own profit, it never ceaſeth to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe until it attain to perfection: For we ſee naturally come to paſs in Plants and living Creatures, and all things, that they never ceaſe growing until they come to ripe age; ſo it comes to paſs, that we proceed ſo far as to love God, not becauſe he is good to us, but becauſe he is good; even as by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture we love thoſe things which be beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for very names ſake, though no profit
<pb facs="tcp:121281:9"/>redound to us: Now the beauty of God is goodneſs it ſelf, beſides which none ought to be loved, either for reward or fear of puniſhment: This is it which S. <hi>John</hi> calls perfect love; the perfection whereof all the elect of God ſtrive to attain as the chief end; for there is nothing more perfect, and of more antiquity, then the love of God, yea God himſelf is love : Whoſoever hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained this love, is deprived of all <hi>Egoity,</hi> (that I may uſe the words of our Author) and doth love God only as he is good, and all things beſides, which God loves himſelf; that is, all things which are any where, ſin excepted; for there is nothing which God loveth not, except ſin.</p>
            <p>This little Book propoundeth to us the love of God, and doth teach us the way to attain the ſame; Bleſſed is he who valiantly ſtriveth to obtain this price, and doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly run this Race; for if death do meet with him whilſt he is running it, he ſhall die a Souldier of Chriſt, and ſo ſhall be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged of him before his Father: Even as in the Law, <hi>a maid that was betrothed to a man, was eſteemed and called his wife, although as yet they were not come toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> Deut. <hi>22.28, 29.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>JO. THEOPHILUS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:121281:9"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Theologia Germanica,</hi> A Little Golden Book, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing briefly, how to put off the Old Man, and to put on the New.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. I.</hi> What is perfect, and what is imperfect.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Aint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>When that which is perfect is come, then that which is imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and in part ſhall be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed:</hi> Now obſerve what it is to be perfect, and what to be in part; perfect is that thing which in it ſelf, and in that which it is, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth and containeth all things; and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:121281:10"/>wanting which, and without which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing truly is; and wherein all things have that thing which they are; for it is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all things, and is unchangeable and unmoveable in it ſelf, and yet doth change and move all other things.</p>
               <p>But that is imperfect and in part, which hath its being and exiſtence from that which is perfect, even as clearneſs and brightneſs proceeds from the Sun, or from the light, and ſeemeth to be ſomething which is called this or that, and is named a creature, and none of theſe imperfect things is that which is perfect, neither is that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect thing any of thoſe which are imperfect; thoſe things which are imperfect may be comprehended, known and expreſſed, but that which is perfect is incomprehenſible, unknown and unutterable, of all creatures, as they are creatures: Therefore that which is perfect is without name, as being none of thoſe; and a creature, as a creature, cannot know or comprehend it. Now when that which is perfect is come, that which is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect is contemned. But when doth it come? I ſay it cometh when it is ſo far known, perceived and taſted in the mind, as poſſible it can be.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:121281:10"/>
               <p>Here ariſeth a queſtion; ſeeing it is ſuch a thing as cannot be known or comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by any creature, and that the mind is a creature? Then how is it poſſible that the mind ſhould know it? I therefore added, (as it is a creature) as if I ſhould ſay, ſo far as it is a creature framed and created, and ſo far forth as it can be ſaid of it, I, or my ſelf, this is impoſſible unto it; for to the end, that that which is perfect may be known of any creature; it is neceſſary, that very thing which is created and made, and may be called I, or my ſelf, ſhould periſh, and be turned to nothing. This is the meaning of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> when he ſaith, <hi>When that which is perfect is come</hi> (that is, is known) then that which is imperfect (being the ſubſtance of all created things) and whatſoever can be ſaid of them, I, or my ſelf, or mine, all this is to be wholly contemned and counted for nothing: Truly ſo long as we eſteem of that which we call I, and ſo long as we cleave unto it, that which is perfect remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth unknown.</p>
               <p>Some man may object; you ſay there is nothing beſides that which is perfect, or without it, and yet you ſay that ſomething doth flow from it, that then which flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:121281:11"/>from it is without it.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, That beſides it, or without it nothing truly exiſteth, becauſe whatſoever floweth from it is not truly it, nor hath any being but in that which is perfect, and is a certain evident brightneſs or clearneſs; which indeed is nothing, nor hath any being but in the fire, from whence the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs floweth, as we ſee in that Sun and light.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> What is Sin?</head>
               <p>TRuth, Faith, and Scripture faith, that Sin is nothing elſe, but that the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doth divert it ſelf from the immutable God, and adhereth to a mutable, that is, doth turn it ſelf from that which is perfect, to that which is in part and imperfect, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially to it ſelf. —Now this obſerve, when the creature doth challenge any good thing to it ſelf, as to be, to live, to know, briefly, to be able to do any thing that can be termed good, as being in it ſelf that good thing, or as though that good thing were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining unto it, then it averteth it ſelf. What other thing then did the Devil? Or what was his averſion and fall? but that he
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:121281:11"/>did arrogate this unto himſelf, that he was ſomething, and would be ſomething, and that ſomething was his, and in his right and power; this Arrogancy to be I, to my ſelf, to be me, and to be mine, was his averſion and fall, and this is ſtill in uſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. Adams <hi>Sin.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHat did <hi>Adam</hi> Alſo elſe but the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſame? Men are wont to ſay that <hi>Adam</hi> periſhed, becauſe he did eat an apple; I ſay, this happened to him by reaſon of his Arrogancy, for that he aſſumed to himſelf to be I, to me, mine, me, &amp;c. For though he had eaten ſeven apples, if it had not been in regard of his Arrogancy he had not fallen, but when Arrogancy took place he then fell, and ſo he ſhould have done, though he had eaten no apples at all: But let us pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, I have fallen an hundred times more precipitately then <hi>Adam</hi> did, and all men were not able to reſtore the loſs and fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> how then might my fall be correct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or reſtored? ſurely it muſt be helped as the fall of <hi>Adam</hi> was, and by the ſame help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and after the ſame manner.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:121281:12"/>
               <p>How then, and from whom procedes this amendment? neither could man do it without God, nor was God bound to do it without man: Wherefore God aſſumed the nature of man or humanity and became man, and man was made God, and thus was the amendment made, and ſo muſt my fall be corrected: I cannot do it without God, it is not meet, neither will God do it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out me: For that this might be effected, it was fitting that God in me ſhould alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come man, that thus God ſhould take upon himſelf whatſoever is in me, as well with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me as without me, as nothing might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in me contrary to God, or might hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his work, and though God ſhould aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume all men that are unto himſelf, and ſhould become man in them, and they in him ſhould become God, and the ſame ſhould not be done in me, my fall ſhould never be recovered, nor yet my ſin done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, except the ſame were alſo done in me: neither know I, nor am I able to give my furtherance towards this amendment and recovery, but only I muſt ſuffer and be pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, and God only the agent and doer; I ſuffering his work and will, which becauſe I will not ſuffer, but will my ſelf be I, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:121281:12"/>to me, and mine, this hindered God, that he could not work without diſturbance, and ſo comes it to paſs, that my fall and averſion remaineth unamended, and all this falleth out by reaſon of my Arrogancy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> That all good is only Gods.</head>
               <p>GOD ſaith, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 42. Mine honor will I give to none, which is as much as if he ſhould ſay, that honor and glory is due to none but God only, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. Therefore if I do arrogate any goodneſs to my ſelf, as that I am, can do any thing that I know, that I work, of that any thing is mine, or done of me, or done to me, arrogating ſuch things to my ſelf, and turning them to my honor and glory, then I do doubly offend: for firſt I fall and avert my ſelf as hath been formerly ſaid; next I deprive God of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in attributing that to my ſelf which is proper only to God; for whatſoever ought to be called good, that is due to none but only to the eternal and true good, which is God. And whoſoever doth arrogate that unto himſelf, doth unrighteouſly, and againſt God</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:121281:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of the putting off the Old Man.</head>
               <p>SOme men ſay, that a man ought to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come void of wiſdom, will, deſire, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, and all other things, which is not to be underſtood, that in man there ſhould be no knowledg, or that God ſhould not be known, loved, willed, deſired, praiſed, or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored in him, for this were a mighty fault, and man ſhould become like to a beaſt: but we muſt proceed ſo far, that our knowledg may be ſo clear and perfect as to underſtand that this knowledg belongeth neither unto man nor unto the creature, but unto the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Wiſdom, about which is the eternal Word; and thus man and the creature va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth, and doth not arrogate to its ſelf as its own; and the leſs knowledg that the creature doth arrogate, it becometh the more perfect: the like we muſt conceive of will, love, deſire, and all ſuch things, for the leſs that man doth arrogate theſe to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, the nobler, the excellenter, and diviner he becometh; and the more he doth aſſume theſe unto himſelf, ſo much he is made the more blockiſh, baſe and imperfect. Thus then ought man to become void of al things,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:121281:13"/>that is, not to arrogate them to himſelf: When then man in this manner is made void of theſe, it comes to paſs that this is the moſt excellent and cleareſt knowledg that can be in man, and the excellenteſt love and deſire; the cauſe whereof is this, All things being only Gods, it is better and more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent that they ſhould appertain to God then to any creature; and the cauſe why I do challenge any goodneſs to my ſelf, is by reaſon that I ſuppoſe that it is mine, or that I am it: If I knew the truth, I ſhould alſo know that the thing is not mine, nor that I am it; it proceeds not from me, &amp;c. and ſo mine Arrogancy would fall to nothing. It is better that God, or that which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to God, ſhould be known, loved, prayed and honored as much as may be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, and that man ſhould conceive that he doth praiſe or love God, then that God ſhould not be praiſed, loved, honored and known; for when opinion and ignorance are turned to knowledg and underſtanding of this, then Arrogancy vaniſheth; for a man will then ſay on this wiſe, Wretch and fool that I am, I ſuppoſed my ſelf to be that thing, but now I perceive that it was and is God only.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:121281:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> How the life of Man is to be compoſed.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>BOetius</hi> ſaith, it is our fault that we do not love that which is beſt, and herein he ſaith the truth, for that which is beſt ought moſt to be loved, and in this love no reſpect is to be had of profit or diſprofit, gain or loſs, honor or reproach, praiſe or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praiſe, or any ſuch things, but that which in very truth is the moſt excellent and beſt; the ſame ought alſo to be deareſt unto us, and that for no other end, but that it is beſt and moſt excellent: According to it a man might compoſe his life both externally and internally; externally, becauſe among thoſe things that are created, one thing is better then another, as the eternal good doth ſhine more in one then in another, in which thing therefore that eternal good doth moſt of all ſhine, is brighteſt, worketh, is known and admired; that among all creatures is moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent: alſo, where it is leſs apparent, that likewiſe is the leſs good. Seeing therefore that man is converſant with the creatures, doth uſe them, and knows their difference; he ought to eſteem that which is beſt, to be moſt dear, and to cleave unto it, and to unite
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:121281:14"/>himſelf thereto, and eſpecially unto thoſe things which are attributed unto God as his, and belongeth unto him, ſuch as are his goodneſs, truth, peace, love and juſtice; and according unto theſe the outward man ought to frame his life, and to deſpiſe and fly all things which are contrary unto them: But if the inward man by a jump, as it were, will ſtep into that which is perfect, that which is perfect will be found and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived to be boundleſly, infinitely and innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merably more excellent and better then whatſoever is imperfect and in part; alſo the eternal, more then the tranſitory; and the fountain and beginning, more then all things which flow or can proceed from it: and ſo that which is imperfect, and in part, ſhall be unpleaſant and become aboliſhed. This ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to the end, that that which is excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and the beſt, may be alſo held the dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt; it is requiſite that this be done.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Of the two Eyes of Chriſt.</head>
               <p>WE muſt conſider that which is read and ſaid, that the Soul of Chriſt had two eyes, the one the right, the other the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:121281:15"/>left: In the beginning when things were created, the right eye did turn it ſelf into E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity and Divinity, and there ſtood un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable in perfect contemplation, and uſe of divine Nature, and divine perfection, and remained unmoved, free from all falling, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, motion, grief, pain, and torment, which happen to the outward man: with his left eye he beheld things created, and did know the difference, and did underſtand what was better and worſe, more noble and more baſe, and in this manner the outward man of Chriſt was framed: Thus ſtood the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man of Chriſt, according to the right eye of his Soul, in the perfect uſe of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine nature, in perfect pleaſure and joy; but the outward man, and the left eye of the Soul was with him in pain and calamity, and perfect labour; and ſo it came to paſs, that that inward or right eye remain'd unmoved, not hindred, free from all labour, pain and torment, which happened to the outward man. It is ſaid, that when Chriſt was whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped at the pillar, and did hang on the Croſs, according to the outward man, his ſoul, or his inward man did ſtand according to the right eye in perfect uſe of the divine nature, and in as high a condition of pleaſure and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:121281:15"/>joy as after he aſcended into Heaven, and is now: Alſo that his outward man, or his ſoul, according to the left eye in this work in all things which did belong unto him, as concerning outward things, was not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred or damnified by the internal, neither of them depending on the other.</p>
               <p>Now the created ſoul of man, it hath alſo two eyes, the one in the power of beholding eternity, the other in looking upon time, and things created, to know the difference, as before hath been ſaid, and to give life to the body: But theſe two eyes of the ſoul of man cannot do their work together; for, that the ſoul with the right eye might behold eternity, it is neceſſary that the left eye do abate all his works, and ſo carry it ſelf as if it were dead: Alſo, that the left eye might perform all his work, and be employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in outward things, and is in pain, and things created, it is neceſſary that the right eye be employed in contemplation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Whether in this life eternal life may be taſted.</head>
               <p>IT is a queſtion whether the ſoul, whilſt it is in the body, may proceed ſo far as to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:121281:16"/>behold eternity, and receive a taſte of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life and everlaſting happineſs. Uſually it is denyed, and ſo it is true, if you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it after this manner: So long as the ſoul doth behold the body, and thoſe things that belong to the body, as time, and things which are created, and doth conform and mingle himſelf with them, this cannot be; for to the end the ſoul may diſcern or behold eternity, it is neceſſary that it be pure and free from all reſemblances, and from all things created, and eſpecially that it be ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from it ſelf: And this thing never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fell in this life. But S. <hi>Dennis</hi> thinks it may be done, as may be gathered out of his words to <hi>Timothy,</hi> which ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> theſe; <hi>To behold Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ſecrets,</hi> it is neceſſary that thou aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don thy ſences, and whatſoever can be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the ſenſes, reaſon alſo, and the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of reaſon, and whatſoever can be perceived and known by reaſon, whether it be created or uncreated, and that thou go and paſs out of thy ſelf, and from the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of all theſe things which I have men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, and ſo come into that one unity of him who is above all nature and knowledg: thus far he. Now if this could not befall man, why doth he teach it, or why doth he
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:121281:16"/>ſpeak to man in this life? Yea, further know, that a certain Maſter ſaith upon theſe words of <hi>Dennis,</hi> That it doth come to paſs, that it doth often befall man, that he verily think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that he doth ſee and behold it as often as he will; and there is no ſuch aſpect, but that it is more excellent, dearer to God, and more worthy then whatſoever all things created, as created, can perform.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> That good, except it be in man, cannot make men happy.</head>
               <p>VVE muſt eſpecially obſerve and know, that no creature, no good; no, not the good it ſelf, which is God, doth make man, or the ſoul indued with vertue, good or bleſſed, ſo long as it is without the ſoul; and the ſame we muſt think of ſin or malice: and therefore although it be a good thing to enquire &amp; ſearch, and alſo to know what good men have done or ſuffered, how they have lived, and what God in them, or by them, hath done or willed; yet it is a hundred times better that a man ſhould ſearch &amp; know, what, and of what kind the ſtate of his own life is, and what God is, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:121281:17"/>would, and doth in him, and in what thing God is willing or unwilling to uſe him: Therefore this alſo is true, which is ſaid, that it is never ſo good to go abroad, but it is better to remain at home: This alſo is to be known, that eternal happineſs is in that only one, and none other; and that man, or his ſoul, ſhould either be, or become bleſſed: It is neceſſary that that only thing ſhould be in the ſoul. Some will ask, what is that one good? I anſwer, it is good, or to be made good, and yet it is neither this nor that good which can be named, known, or ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but all, and above all: neither is it need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful that it ſhould now again enter into the ſoul, for it is already in it, though unknown: When it is ſaid, that it is meet we ſhould come unto it, and that it ſhould come into the ſoul, it is as much as if you ſhould ſay, we ought to ſeek it, have the ſeeking of it, and ſmell it out: And becauſe it is but one, unity and ſimplicity is better then mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude; for bleſſedneſs is not placed in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and multitude, but in one and unity; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it in many things created, or in the work of any created thing (that I may ſpeak briefly) but bleſſedneſs is only placed in God, and his work; wherefore I ought to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:121281:17"/>have reſpect to God and his work only, and to relinquiſh all natural things with their works, and chiefly my ſelf; yea, further, all works, or miracles, which either God hath done or ever may do, in or by the nature of all things; yea alſo, God himſelf, with all his goodneſs, as he is without me, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to me, doth not make me bleſſed, but as he is within me, and is known, loved, felt, and perceived by me.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Of the deſire of thoſe who be illuminated.</head>
               <p>NOw it is to be obſerved, that thoſe that be illuminated with that true light, do know that whatſoever they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves can deſire or make choice of, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever hath been deſired, choſen, or known at any time of any creature, at all, (as it is a creature) is nothing, if it be compared to that eternal good: Again, forſaking all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires and choice, they do commit and refer themſelves and all their actions to the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal good, then there remaineth in them a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to advance and bring themſelves nearer to the eternal good, that is, to a nearer knowledg and more ardent love, and a more
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:121281:18"/>ready ſubmiſſion, and to an entire ſubjection and obedience. So that every illuminate man may be able to ſay of this manner, I could wiſh I were the ſame to the eternal good that a mans hand is to himſelf: And ſuch men do always fear that they are not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſufficiently ſubject unto it, they do al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo deſire the ſalvation of all men, and yet are they free from this deſire; neither do they challenge it to themſelves, as underſtanding ſufficiently that this deſire belongeth not to man, but to the eternal good; for whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is good, that no man ought to arrogate to himſelf, becauſe it belongeth to the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal good: Beſides theſe kind of men live in freedom, ſo that without fear, either of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, or hell, or hope of reward, or of the Kingdom of Heaven, they do live in meer ſubjection and obedience of the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal good, and that with a free love: This was perfectly in Chriſt, and is in his follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, in ſome more, in ſome leſs.</p>
               <p>It is a miſerable thing, that whereas the eternal good doth furniſh and ſtir us up to that which is moſt excellent, we are unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to entertain it; for what is more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent then true ſpiritual poverty, and yet when it is ſet before us we will none of it?
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:121281:18"/>We would be (as I may ſo ſpeak) over-wily, ſo that if we but feel a delicate taſte, ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and pleaſure in our ſelves, we think it is well with us, and that we love God; but if this be wanting, we are in ſorrow and do forget God, and think we are undone, which is a great fault &amp; an ill ſign: for a true lover doth as much love God, and the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal good? in want as in plenty, &amp; alike in bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs as in pleaſure, and ſo in the reſt. Let every man examine himſelf in theſe things.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> Of Hell, and of the Kingdom of Heaven.</head>
               <p>THe Soul of Chriſt was to deſcend into Hell before it could aſcend into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and the ſame muſt befall the ſoul of man. But conſider how this muſt be done: This then comes to paſs when a man know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and beholdeth himſelf, and findeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſo evil, as that he is unworthy of all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and good that might befall him from God or the creature: Further, he thinketh nothing elſe of himſelf but that he is perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually damned and loſt, and that to be leſs then he is worthy of: Further, he thinks himſelf worthy of more calamities then can
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:121281:19"/>befall him in this life; and that it is right and juſt that all things ſhould fall croſs upon him, and bring grief and torment to him, all which is leſs then he deſerveth; yea, he ſuppoſeth it to be juſt that he ſhould be damned for ever, and become the footſtool of all the Devils in Hell: all which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding is leſs then he is worthy of. Neither will he, nor can he conceive any comfort or deliverance either from God or from the creatures, but is willing to want comfort and deliverance; neither doth he way wardly bear damnation and pain, for that it is equal, juſt, and not contrary to God, but agreeing to Gods will; therefore he doth love it, and take it in good part, not bearing unwillingly any thing but his own ſin and ungodlineſs, becauſe that is unjuſt and contrary to God: this doth grieve and trouble his mind, &amp; this is called the true pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitence for ſin; and he that doth in this life ſo come into Hell, the ſame man after this life doth come into the Kingdom of Heaven, and in this life doth attain ſuch a taſte as paſſeth all the joy and pleaſure, as either hath or can befall a man in this life from any tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral thing: and as long as a man is thus in Hell, neither God nor the creature can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:121281:19"/>him, even as it is written, <hi>In Hell there is no redemption;</hi> of this thing one ſaid, <hi>I periſh, I die, I live without comfort, being damned both within and without; I deſire of none that I may be delivered:</hi> Now God hath not forſaken man in this Hell, but ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth him to himſelf; ſo as man deſireth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the eternal good, and underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the eternal good to be above meaſure good, and this is his pleaſure, peace, joy, reſt and ſatisfaction: and when man doth not regard nor deſire any thing but the eternal good, and nothing in or concerning himſelf, it comes to paſs that the peace, joy, reſt, pleaſure, and all ſuch like things as do belong to the eternal good, become mans, and ſo man is in the Kingdom of Heaven.</p>
               <p>This Hell and this Kingdom of Heaven are two good and ſafe ways for man in this life, which whoſoever doth find out rightly and well, is happy; for this Hell hath an end, but this Kingdom of Heaven doth remain for ever. Beſides man muſt mark that whilſt he is in this Hell nothing can comfort him, neither can he think that ever he ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered or comforted again: When he is in this Kingdom of Heaven there is nothing can hurt or object him, neither doth he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:121281:20"/>that he can be hurt or diſcomforted, and yet, after this Hell he is comforted and delivered, and after this Heaven he is trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled and deprived of comfort: Now this Hell and this heavenly Kingdom doth befall man, ſo as that he knoweth not when it cometh; neither can a man, by his own means, do or omit any thing whereby they ſhould either come or depart from him; neither can man give or take away from himſelf either of theſe, or take or loſe them; but it comes to paſs here, as it is written, <hi>John</hi> 3.8. <hi>The wind</hi> (or ſpirit) <hi>bloweth where it liſteth, and thou hearest the ſound thereof</hi> (that is, when it is preſent) <hi>but knoweſt not whence it co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, nor whither it goeth.</hi> And when man is in either of theſe, he is in good caſe, and he may be as ſafe in Hell as in the Kingdom of Heaven: and ſo long as a man is in this life, he may often paſs out of the one into the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yea, within a day and a night, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times oftner, and that without himſelf: but when man is in neither of theſe, he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant with the creature, and wandreth hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and thither, and knows not which way to turn him; wherefore he ought never to let theſe two things go out of his mind.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:121281:20"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> Of true Peace.</head>
               <p>MAny ſay that they can have no peace nor reſt, but are in continual conflict with many adverſities, calamities, griefs and ſorrows: If you will conſider the truth of this matter after this manner, the very Devil might have peace, if all things were carried after his will and choice: For this cauſe we muſt mark and obſerve the peace which Chriſt did leave unto his Diſciples at his laſt paſſage, when he ſaith, <hi>My peace I give unto you, not ſuch as the world giveth give I unto you,</hi> for the world deceiveth with her gifts. But what peace then is that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Chriſt ſpeaketh? Surely that which is (inward) which doth pierce and break through all calamities, adverſities, troubles, miſeries and infamies, and all ſuch like; ſo as a man in all theſe ſhould be joyful and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient as Chriſts Diſciples were; and not they, but alſo all the elect friends of God, and all the true imitators of Chriſt: Wherefore per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade thy ſelf, if any man confer his love, diligence and endeavours in and upon theſe things, he may ſufficiently know the true and eternal peace (which is God) as much
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:121281:21"/>as is poſſible for a creature.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thaulerus</hi> ſaith, <hi>There are ſome in this life, who over-ſoon forſake their imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons before the truth hath freed them from them; and becauſe they do ſet themſelves at liberty, therefore can they hardly, or not at all, attain to the truth.</hi> The work of God then, and his Commandment moving and admoniſhing, ought always to be dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently obſerved, and not the work, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and admonition of men. Now we muſt know that no man can be illuminated except he firſt be purged, cleanſed and freed: and further, that no man can be united with God, except he firſt be illuminated; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there are three ways, firſt, purgation; ſecondly, illumination; and thirdly, union.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> Of the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> and the amendment by Chriſt.</head>
               <p>WHatſoever dyed and was loſt in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> the ſame quickned and revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved again in Chriſt: Likewiſe whatſoever did riſe and live in <hi>Adam,</hi> the ſame periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and dyed in Chriſt: But what is that? I ſay, it is true obedience and diſobedience. And what is true obedience? I ſay it is this,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:121281:21"/>a man ought ſo far to conſiſt and to be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely without himſelf, and what may be termed his own, that is, without ſelf-will, (and as I may ſo ſpeak, being I) that he ſeeks and eſteems himſelf, and what he is in all matters, no more then if he were not at all; and that he conceives no better of himſelf, nor eſteems no more of himſelf, and all that is his, and all creatures, then if he were not at all. What then is that thing which is to be eſteemed and valued? I anſwer, it is that only one thing which is called God, and this is true obedience in verity; and ſo it falls out in bleſſed eternity, that in it nothing is ſought, eſteemed, of loved, but that one; not any thing accounted worthy, but the ſame one: From whence it may be gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed what diſobedience is, <hi>(viz.)</hi> when a man doth attribute any thing to himſelf, or ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth that he is ſomething, knoweth and is able to do ſomething, and regardeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and his own ends in buſineſs, loveth himſelf, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Man was and is created unto true obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. and doth ow the ſame unto God; and as this obedience was loſt and periſhed in <hi>Adam,</hi> ſo it revived and flour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhed
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:121281:22"/>again in Chriſt: But diſobedience a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe and lived in <hi>Adam,</hi> but dyed in Chriſt. And ſurely the humanity of Chriſt was, and conſiſteth ſo far forth wholy and entirely without it ſelf &amp; all other things, as no other creature conſiſted at anytime in like manner, and was none other thing but a certain manſion and habitation of God: And what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever belonged to God, or appertained to that humanity, had life, and was a certain habitation of God: of theſe it never chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged any thing to it ſelf; nay, it did not challenge the very Divinity to it ſelf, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of it was a habitation; nor any of thoſe things which the Divinity willed, or refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in it; nor any of thoſe things which in the humanity either befel and were ſuffered: ſo as in the humanity there was neither ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation, ſeeking, nor deſire, ſaving only a ſeeking and deſire, how and after what manner it might ſatisfie the Divinity, and that very deſire the humanity did not attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute unto it ſelf. Of this knowledg more cannot be ſpoken or writ in this place, for it is unſpeakable; neither was it ever yet diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, nor ſhall be fully expreſſed; for it is ſuch a thing as cannot be ſpoken or writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, but of him who is the ſelf-ſame thing, and knoweth it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:121281:22"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIV.</hi> What the old and new Man is.</head>
               <p>THis is alſo to be obſerved: when men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is made of the old and new man, the matter is thus to be underſtood; the old man is <hi>Adam,</hi> diſobedience, ſelfneſs, egoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, &amp;c. But the new man is Chriſt and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience. When we ſpeak of dying, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing, and the like, you muſt thus under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it: It is neceſſary that the old man be brought to nought; and when and where this comes to paſs in the divine light, there the new man is born again: alſo when it is ſaid, That man muſt dye in himſelf, it is as much as if you ſhould ſay, it is neceſſary that himſelf, or egoity ſhould dye: S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Put off the old man with his works, and put on the new man, who is made and formed according unto God:</hi> He that lives in ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and according to the old man, he is, and is called the ſon of <hi>Adam,</hi> and hath power moſt eſpecially and in very truth to live with him; and is alſo the ſon and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Devil: but he that liveth in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, and in the new man, he is the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Chriſt and the Son of God.</p>
               <p>Now when the old man dyeth, and the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:121281:23"/>new man is born, there thence ariſeth a new birth, of which Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Except ye be born again, ye ſhall not enter into the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God:</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> alſo ſaith, <hi>Even as in</hi> Adam <hi>all men do dye, even ſo in Chriſt all are revived.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever doth follow <hi>Adam</hi> in diſobedience, they are dead, and ſhall never live again, but in Chriſt, that is, in obedience; the cauſe is this, as long as man is <hi>Adam,</hi> or his ſon, he is without God: Chriſt ſaith, <hi>He that is not with me, is againſt me:</hi> he therefore that is againſt God is dead before God, but he that is with Chriſt in obedience, he is, and liveth with God: This is alſo written, ſin is this, when the creature doth avert it ſelf from the Creator, and is like unto it, and the very ſame. For whoſoever is in diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience is in ſin, neither ſhall ſin ever be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected or amended, but by turning to obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; and as long as man liveth in diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, ſin is never corrected nor amended in him, do what he can, which is to be known by this, becauſe diſobedience is ſin it ſelf. But if man do return to true obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, all faults are corrected, amended, and pardoned, but otherwiſe this cannot come to paſs.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:121281:23"/>
               <p>A matter worthy to be obſerved, yea, if the Devil could come to true obedience, he ſhould become an Angel, and all his ſin and wickednes ſhould be corrected, &amp; amended, and at once forgiven; Alſo if any Angel could return to diſobedience, he ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently become a Devil, although he ſhould do no other thing.</p>
               <p>If it could come to paſs, that any man might wholy and abſolutely caſt off him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, ſo as that he lived without all things in true obedience, as the humanity of Chriſt was, then he ſhould be voyd of himſelf and one with Chriſt, and ſhould be the ſame by grace which Chriſt was by nature: But men deny that this can be done, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſay, no man is voyd of ſin; howſoever it be, this is evident, that the neerer any man approacheth to this obedience, ſo much the leſs ſin is in him; and the further he is from it, the more ſin he hath: Finally, that a man ſhould be good, better, or the beſt of all; evil, worſe, or the worſt of all, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, or bleſſed of God; all conſiſteth in this obedience or diſobedience. This alſo is written, the more ſelfneſs and egoity, the more there is of ſin and unrighteouſneſs; and the leſſer there is of the one, the greater
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:121281:24"/>want there is of the other: This alſo is written, the more that my ſelf doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe (that is, egoity or ſelfneſs) the more doth in me increaſe the I of God, <hi>id eſt,</hi> God himſelf.</p>
               <p>If all men were in true obedience, there would be then no pain nor miſery, but only that which is perceived by the ſenſes, and that ſhould be very eaſie and not to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of: which may be thus proved, for if that ſhould come to paſs all men would be in concord, neither would one grieve or hurt another, neither would any man live or do any thing which were contrary to God: whence therefore could grief and miſery come? But now alas, all the World, and men in the World, are in diſobedience; and if any man were wholy and ſincerely o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient, as we beleeve that Chriſt was, and as he was indeed (elſe he could not have been Chriſt) all men would be diſobedient to this man, and would put him to all bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs and miſerable ſorrow, for all men would be contrary to him, which we may underſtand by this; For that man in this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience ſhould be one with God, and God himſelf ſhould be there man himſelf. Now all diſobedience is contrary to God, and is
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:121281:24"/>nothing elſe; In very deed there is nothing contrary unto God, neither creature nor work of the creature, nor whatſoever can be named or thought, there are none of theſe I ſay, contrary unto God, or that can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe him, but only diſobedience: But a diſobedient man is ſo diſpleaſant unto him, and contrary, and God complaineth ſo much of him, that when as man doth grieve and hath a feeling of thoſe things which be contrary to him, that God would willingly endure an hundred deaths that he might kill diſobedience in man, and beget there again his own obedience: And although no man be ſo wholy and ſo ſincere in this obedience as Chriſt was, yet it may come to paſs, that ſome may approach ſo neer unto it as to be made and called, and ſo to be Divine and God: And the neerer that man doth come unto it, and the more he is made Divine and God, all diſobedience, ſin and injuſtice is the more troubleſome to him, and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth him, being hard to be endured. Diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience and ſin is the ſame thing, there is no ſin but diſobedience, and that which proceedeth from it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:121281:25"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> That a man ought to attribute good to God, and evil to himſelf.</head>
               <p>OBſerve that which now ſhall be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: there be ſome men which do ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and ſay, that they are ſo far mortified, and gone out of themſelves, that they may lead a life voyd of ſorrow, and free from all grievances; even as if all men were in this obedience, or as if they were no creatures: Alſo that they may lead an eaſie and ſweet life whereby to pleaſe their minds, and in all things whatſoever give themſelves wholy unto pleaſure; but ſurely it is not ſo, for, their eſtate is no other then before is ſaid: It is true, it would be ſo, if all men were indued with obedience, but they are not ſo; and again, this alſo cannot be: But ſome man will ſay, ſurely man ought to be free from all things, and not to attribute any thing unto himſelf, which is either bad or good. I anſwer, no man ought to attribute any good unto himſelf, for that is proper only to God and his goodneſs; but that man hath grace and eternal reward, who is fitted thereunto, being apt and prepared to be the houſe and habitation of the eternal
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:121281:25"/>good and Divinity, ſo as it may exerciſe in him, without hinderance, the power, will, and work of it ſelf; but if man will exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe himſelf, and attribute none evil unto himſelf, but decline to the devil and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, then I ſay, that blame, and Infamy, and eternal miſ-fortune, and damnation, is due to ſuch a man, for that he is fitted, and prepared, and accommodated unto this, that the devil, deceit, lying, and all other wickedneſs, might have the full ſcope, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, work and diſcourſe in him, and that he might be the houſe and habitation thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVI.</hi> That the Chriſtian life is the beſt.</head>
               <p>WE ought alſo to obſerve, beleeve and know, that no life is ſo excellent, good, and ſo beloved of God, as the life of Chriſt, which notwithſtanding is the moſt bitter life to all nature and ſelfnes; alſo a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute &amp; free life is moſt pleaſant to nature, and ſelfneſs, and egoity: yet it is not the beſt and moſt excellent, but it may be made the beſt in ſome men: and although the life of Chriſt be moſt bitter, yet it is the beſt beloved of all, as from hence may appear,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:121281:26"/>becauſe that is the knowledg whereby the true and ſimple good is diſcerned, which good is not this or that, but the ſame wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>When that which is perfect and entire is come, then all diviſion and imperfection ſhall be aboliſhed:</hi> which ſentence of his is thus to be taken; That w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is perfect, is ſuperior to all diviſion; and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thing which is divided and imperfect, is nothing in compariſon of that which is perfect. Thus alſo ſhall all knowledge of that which is divided be aboliſhed: when and where that which is perfect is known, it is needful alſo that it be ſo loved; and that the other love wherewith a man doth love himſelf and all other things, be wholy aboliſhed: and this knowledg doth alſo diſcern what is beſt and moſt excellent in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing, and loveth that in the true good, and for none other cauſe but for the true good: and where this knowledg is, there is perceived that the life of Chriſt is beſt and moſt excellent, and therefore alſo to be loved of all, and willingly had and born, not regarding whether it be ſweet or ſowre, acceptable or troubleſome to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Beſides, it is to be obſerved, that in what man this true good is known, there
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:121281:26"/>it is neceſſary that the life of Chriſt ſhould be, and remain unto the death of the body; he that thinketh othewiſe is deceived, and he that ſpeaketh otherwiſe, lyeth; and in whom the life of Chriſt is not, he neither knoweth the true God, nor Truth it ſelf.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVII.</hi> Of the way to Chriſt.</head>
               <p>LEt no man conceive that he can attain to this true light and knowledg, and to the life of Chriſt, by many queſtions, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, reading, or ſtudying, or by excellent hard ſciences, and learning, or exquiſite na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural reaſon: I will ſay further, ſo long as man retaineth any thing of any thing, or doth hold any thing in eſteem, love, deſire, or ſtudy it, or keepeth it in his hands, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever that is, whether it be man himſelf or any thing elſe, he attaineth not to this: This Chriſt affirmeth, when he ſaith, <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> 16. <hi>If thou wilt follow me, forſake thy ſelf and come after me.</hi> And he that doth not forſake himſelf and his own life, and doth not leave and loſe it, is not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of me, neither can he be my Diſciple:
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:121281:27"/>The meaning of which words is this, he that doth not forſake and abandon all things, can never know me truly, nor attain to my life: And ſay, that this had never bin uttered by the mouth of man, yet truth ſpeaketh by it ſelf, for this is as true as truth it ſelf: But ſo long as man doth love in part, and a portion only, and eſpecially him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and doth make account and eſteem of it, he is ſo far blinded, and becometh ſo blind, as that he knoweth not good, but ſuch as is moſt profitable, commodious and pleaſing to himſelf, and thoſe things which are his, this I ſay he chiefly accounteth of, and holdeth moſt dear.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVIII.</hi> That the life of Chriſt is envyed of humane wiſdom.</head>
               <p>ANd becauſe the life of Chriſt is moſt bitter to all ſelfneſs and egoity, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for the obtaining of the ſame, it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that all ſelfneſs and natural egoity, periſh, die, and be utterly forſaken. Therefore alſo every mans nature doth abhor this life, ſuppoſing it to be evil, unjuſt, &amp; fooliſh, and embracing a life fiting it ſelf &amp; pleaſant, and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:121281:27"/>ſuch is his blindneſs that he doth hold it for the beſt. You ſee that there is no life ſo pleaſant and agreeable to nature, as that which conſiſteth of liberty and diſſolate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: Therefore nature cleaveth to this, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying it as her own fleſh, peace and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity; as alſo all things which are her own. And this comes to paſs eſpecially in them who are endued with excellent natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral reaſon; for this doth climb ſo high, and ſtandeth ſo far in her own light, and on her ſelf, as that ſhe thinketh her ſelf to be that eternal and true light, and doth challenge to her ſelf to be the ſame; and being deceived in her ſelf, deceiveth others with her ſelf, who know no better, being thereto alſo enclined.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIX.</hi> The ſtate of a Chriſtian is not to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſled.</head>
               <p>HEre ſome man will ask in what eſtate that man is who followeth the true light as much as is poſſible to him? To whom I will anſwer, that this can never truly be ſaid: and why ſo? becauſe that he who is not the thing, cannot ſay it; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:121281:28"/>can he that is it, and knoweth it, ſpeak it: But if any deſire to know it, let him ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, until he be that thing.</p>
               <p>Further, I beleeve that his outward con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation and manners are ſuch that he is capable of whatſoever is fitting and conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to be done, and whatſoever is not meet and convenient to be done: But is there not ſome luſt of man, who ſaith, ſo I will, ſo I command? this he is not capable of; but man perſwadeth himſelf that many things are fitting and ought to be done, which notwithſtanding are foul and not meet to be done: If a mans own pride, or covetouſneſs, or any other vice, or diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, provoke him to do or omit any thing, he ſaith, that neceſſity urged him to it, and that it ought to be done: if the favor or friendſhip of men, or his own luſt, do ſet him forward to this or that, or doth draw him from it, he ſaith, ſo it is meet and ought to be, and all theſe things are falſe. But if man had none other (muſt or ought) but that which God (our preſerver and truth) doth draw and turn us to, he ſhould ſometimes have more buſineſs and work then now he hath.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:121281:28"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XX.</hi> That the World is mad.</head>
               <p>IT is ſaid that the Devil and his ſpirit doth ſometimes ſo poſſeſs and hold ſome man, as that he knows not what he doth, leaveth undone, being beſides himſelf, the evil ſpirit having ſuch command over him, as that in him, with him, and through him, and from him, he doth or omitteth what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he will. This in ſome ſort is true, that the whole world is poſſeſſed with the Devil, and carryed of him, that is, by lyes, deceits, and other wickedneſſes and vices, which are all diabolical. If therefore any man were in ſuch manner poſſeſſed, and tranſported by the Spirit of God, as that he knew not what he did, or did not, or were ſo out of himſelf, as that the will and Spirit of God ſhould moderate his actions, and ſo govern and move him, as to cauſe him, with him, and from him, whatſoever he would and how he would, then this man were one of thoſe of whom Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>Romans</hi> 8. <hi>Whoſoever are car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed and moved by the Spirit of God, the ſame are the ſons of God, and not ſubjects to the Law:</hi> and to whom Chriſt ſaith,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:121281:29"/>
                  <hi>it is not you that ſpeak, but the Spirit of Chriſt ſpeaketh in you:</hi> but I fear that there are a hundred thouſand, or rather, ſo many as cannot be numbered, who are moved by the Devil; whereas, in the mean time, not one is moved by the Spirit of God, which cometh to paſs, becauſe men have more likeneſs to the Devil then to God : for egoity and ſelfneſs belong wholy to the Devil.</p>
               <p>Now in one or two words, all things may be here expreſſed, which I have here rehearſed in ſo many words, Even thus: Be thou wholy and plainly without thy ſelf. And yet this matter is more fully and better declared, and ſhewed, and diſtinguiſhed in many words.</p>
               <p>Now ſome man will ſay, I am unprepared for all theſe things, therefore this cannot be done in me: and ſo men do get and find out ſome excuſe: To the which we may thus an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; That man is not ready and is unprepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, it is certainly his own fault: For if man would mind and do nothing elſe, but in all things attend his preparation, and endeavor that he might be prepared, ſurely God would prepare him ſufficiently, and would add ſo much love, diligence and ſtudy to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:121281:29"/>that preparation, as ſould be ſufficient to pour into him (being now prepared) all thoſe good things; yet there are certain ways which lead us hither, according to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſaying; If any man deſire to learn any Art whereof he is ignorant, there are four things required to the learning of it: The firſt (which of all other is moſt neceſſary) is a great deſire, diligence and endeavor conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually that it may be done; if this be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, the matter will never be attained. The ſecond is, that you have ſomething, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to learn. The third, that you carefully and diligently obſerve, attend and reverence your Maſter. The fourth, that your ſelf do alſo enterprize and exerciſe that thing. And if any of theſe be wanting, you ſhall never be able to learn or obtain the Art. Even ſuch is the manner of this preparation; and he that hath the firſt, <hi>id eſt,</hi> diligence, and a continual and ſerious deſire to gain the end, he doth ſeek and find all things which appertain, are neceſſary and profit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able for him: And he that uſeth not dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and doth neither love nor deſire, he on the other ſide doth not ſeek, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth not find, and without doubt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth unprepared, nor ever cometh to the end.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:121281:30"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXI.</hi> Of the way unto the life of Chriſt.</head>
               <p>THere are certain ways and preparations preſcribed likewiſe towards this, which are, that we ought to be Gods patients, and to yeeld obedience, duty and ſubjection un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, which is true; for if any man could attain unto the end, which may be had and compaſſed in this life, he ſhould be truly and perfectly endued with all theſe things. But he that ought and will ſuffer God, muſt alſo ſuffer all things; that is, God and himſelf, and the nature of all things, none excepted: And he that ought and will be obedient, ſubject, and dutiful unto God, muſt expreſs his obedience, duty and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection only by ſuffering, and not by doing: alſo all things in general are to be endured and ſuffered of him in ſilence, and by perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance in the inward ſenſes of his mind, and quiet and ſtill bearing: And in all theſe things we ought neither to deſire help, nor to make excuſe, nor to ſtander any, nor to act revenge, but in all things ſay, with a true, loving, and ſubmiſſive mercy, <hi>Father, forgive them, for they know not what they do,</hi> This truly would prove a good way, &amp; an
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:121281:30"/>excellent preparative towards the fartheſt end that man can attain unto in this life, which is the beloved life of Chriſt: For in the life of Chriſt the aforenamed ways exiſt, and are obſerved fully and perfectly, even to the end of the bodily life: wherefore there is none other, either more better or more prepared way for him that loveth the life of Chriſt, then to live and follow the ſame, and to exerciſe himſelf in it, ſo far as he may or can: It is already ſet down in part what is hereunto required; and whatſoever is ſaid, either here, or elſe-where, is all the way, or the means of the way to obtain the right end; but what the end is, no man can tell. If any man deſire to know it, let him go the right way to it, that is, by this life of Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXII.</hi> In what man true Chriſt is.</head>
               <p>YEt are there ways to the life of Chriſt, as we have already ſaid, when, and wherein God and man are joyned together, ſo that it may be truly ſaid, and truth it ſelf may acknowledg it, that the true and perfect God, and true perfect man are one; and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:121281:31"/>man do ſo yeeld &amp; give place unto God, that God himſelf there is man, and that God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo be there preſent, and work alone, and do, and leave undone any thing without any I, to me, mine, and the like; where theſe things are, and exiſt, there is true Chriſt, and no where elſe: Therefore, ſince that here is true and perfect man, here is alſo perfect ſence of pleaſure and pain love &amp; adverſity, and of all things that can be felt or made tryal of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inwardly or outwardly. And becauſe God, there is alſo man himſelf, he can under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand and know love, and other things of that kind: and even as man, who is not God, can feel and know all things which do procure pleaſure and ſorrow to man, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially thoſe things which are contrary to himſelf: after the ſame manner it comes to paſs where God and man are all one, and yet God is man himſelf; there are all things felt which are contrary to God and man; and even as man is there brought to nothing, and God is all, ſo happeneth it to him in that thing which is contrary to man, and doth grief him, that is, it is alſo brought to nothing, and this ought to continue from God as long as corporal and naturalliſe doth endure, and is. This alſo is to be obſerved,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:121281:31"/>that that one thing where God and man are united together, doth conſiſt without it ſelf, and without all things, and is free from all things, that is, it is for God, and not for man, or the creatures; for it is the property of God to conſiſt, and be without this or that, without ſelfneſs, egoity, and the like; but it is the property of the creature to ſeek and will (in all things which it doth or leaveth undone) himſelf, or thoſe things which are his own, and this or that, here or there: When therefore the creature or man doth loſe or lay off his own ſelfneſs or himſelf, it cometh to paſs that God entereth into him with his own (that is) with his ſelfneſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIII.</hi> What it is to be rich in ſpirit.</head>
               <p>THis alſo is to be conſidered, after that man hath paſſed over all that way which leadeth him to the truth, and hath exerciſed himſelf therein, and hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered ſo much affliction; and ſo long, as that now he thinks himſelf wholly ſpent, dead, and gone out of himſelf, and given o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver wholly unto God: Then doth the Devil firſt begin to ſow his ſeed in him, from which feed two fruits ariſe; one of which
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:121281:32"/>is ſpiritual riches or ſpiritual pride; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is inordinate falſe liberty. Theſe are two ſiſters, who ordinarily and willingly frequent together: and this happeneth after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. The devil doth ſo puff up man, as that he doth ſuppoſe he is come to the higheſt exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, ſo as now he ſtands in no more need of Scripture, or any other thing, &amp; generally that he is become ſuch a one as wanteth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: hence there ariſeth in him a great cheerfulnes and peace, whereupon it follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that he ſpeaketh after this manner; go to now, I am above all men, and know and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand more then the whole world; and therefore it is meet and right that I be the God of all creatures, &amp; that al creatures, and eſpecially all men ſhould ſerve me, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip me, and be ſubject to me: this he ſeeketh and deſireth &amp; willingly receiveth from al the creatures, and eſpecially from man, and in his own conceipt he is worthy of all theſe, and thinketh that they are due unto him, and he doth account al men as beaſts, and whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is ſuch as that it can yield unto his body, fleſh &amp; nature, delight, pleaſure, contentment, and chearfulneſs, he thinketh himſelf worthy of it all, and that he ſeeketh and receiveth whenſoever he can obtain it, and he thinks
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:121281:32"/>all too little which he can obtain, ſuppoſing that he is truly worthy of them all; and all men that do ſerve him, and are at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, although they be theeves and robbers, yet he ſaith, that they are noble and faithful hearts, and faithful and charitable to the truth, and towards poor men; and he prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feth, ſeeketh and followeth them whereſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they are. And if any man fail to reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence theſe proud fellows, to obey them, and to be ſubject unto their wills, ſuch a one is not commended of them, but is contemned, although he were as holy as S. <hi>Peter.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when this ſpiritual pride doth ſeem to it ſelf to ſtand in need neither of Scripture<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teaching, nor the like: It cometh to paſs that it doth not ſcorn alone, but alſo deride all Ceremonies, Ordinances, Precepts, Laws, and the very Sacraments of the holy Church: alſo all thoſe men who have theſe orders in uſe, and do attribute any thing unto them: hence it is eaſily perceived that both theſe ſiſters do dwell together. Beſides this, rich man in his pride doth ſometime imagine that he underſtandeth and knoweth more then all men: whence it comes to paſs, that he is forward to ſpeak, and babble more then all other men, and would have his ſayings and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:121281:33"/>talk only in requeſt, and to be heard, and all other mens diſcourſes to be held erronious, or ridiculous and fooliſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIV.</hi> Who be poor in ſpirit.</head>
               <p>BUt where ſpiritual poverty and true ſubmiſſion is, there the matter is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: And this ariſeth hence, becauſe that we truly find and know, that man of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and by his own means, is nothing, and can do nothing, neither is fit for any thing, nor hath any thing but vice and wickedneſs: Hence it comes, that man doth hold himſelf altogether unworthy of theſe things which can befall him from God or from all the creatures, and that in the cauſe of God, and all the creatures, he ought both to ſuffer, and ſometimes to do for Gods ſake; ſo as of himſelf he hath truly right to nothing, but out of the humility of his mind thus he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth: It is meet and convenient that God and al the creatures ſhould be mine enemies, and ſhould cenſure me, and have right againſt me, and I have right to nothing: Hence it is, that this man neither will ask nor regard any thing of God or the creatures, but only
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:121281:33"/>things neceſſary, and that very fearfully, and as by free gift, and not of right: neither doth he afford his body or nature any more good or pleaſure then neceſſity requireth; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth he ſuffer or permit, that any man ſhould help or ſerve him, but in caſe of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, and that is not without fear, becauſe he hath no right to any thing, and ſeemeth unto himſelf unworthy of all things. This man thinketh, that all his words and ſayings are nothing elſe but folly, and therefore he ſpeaketh or talketh with no man in way of teaching, except he be thruſt on with divine love, and even then he doth it with fear, and that as ſparingly as may be.</p>
               <p>It is alſo diſcerned and found out in this ſpiritual poverty and humility, that all men depend wholly and abſolutely on them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, being prone, and ready to commit any ſin and wickedneſs; therefore as it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary and behoveful, that there ſhould be Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, Ceremonies, Laws and Precepts, whereby their blindneſs may be diſcovered, and their ungodlineſs reduced unto order, which if it were not, men would become worſe, and more diſordered then dogs, and other beaſts: Beſides, many men are drawn and converted to the truth by theſe Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:121281:34"/>and Ordinances, which otherwiſe would not be drawn; and ſurely few men attain to the truth, who have not firſt recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Ordinances and Ceremonies, and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed themſelves in them whilſt they knew no other, nor better thing: Hence it is, that Laws and Ordinances are not diſpiſed nor contemned in humility of ſpirit, and ſpiritual poverty, nor men who do uſe and handle them; but out of love and mercy ſuch a man doth complain and lament the caſe of other men with grief on this wiſe: O God of truth, I pour out my complaint before thee, and thou thy ſelf bewayleſt, that mans blindneſs, vice and wickedneſs doth cauſe that to be needful and neceſſary to be done, which notwithſtanding in truth need not be, nor ought to be done. And here is a certain deſire, that men who know nothing better, nor any other means to the truth, might know and underſtand to what end all Laws and Ordinances are, and were made; and this poor man in ſpirit, of whom I ſpeak, doth uſe all theſe things together with other men, which know neither bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, nor any other things, and is partaker of theſe with them; by this means he may keep them from turning themſelves unto evil
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:121281:34"/>things, and that, if it be poſſible, he may bring them nearer.</p>
               <p>Again, whatſoever hath hitherto been ſpoken of poverty and humility, that is truly ſo, and may be made plain and evident by the life &amp; words of Chriſt, who did exerciſe, and perfectly work every act of the humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as it is found in his life, and as he taught by his words, ſaying, <hi>learn of me, becauſe I am meek and lowly of heart;</hi> he did not neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect or deſpiſe the old Law and Diſcipline, nor the men who were ſubject to the Law, yet he ſaid, that it was not ſufficient, but that we muſt go forward, as it is true we ought. S. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo did write, that Chriſt took upon him the Law, that he might free thoſe that were under the Law, that is, bring them to nearer and better things; Chriſt alſo ſaid, <hi>I came not to be ſerved, but to ſerve.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Briefly, in all the deeds, words and life of Chriſt, there is nothing found but true hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility and poverty: And (as I ſaid before) where God is man, and where Chriſt is, there it is neceſſary that this ſhould be: Therefore where pride of mind, and ſpiritual riches, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of a light mind is, there neither is Chriſt nor his true Imitators: Chriſt ſaith, <hi>My ſoul is ſorrowful, even to
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:121281:35"/>the death,</hi> ſpeaking of the death of the body, which came to paſs, becauſe he was born of <hi>Mary,</hi> until the death of his body, and how this was, hath been ſhewed before: Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Bleſſed are the poor in ſpirit,</hi> that is, ſuch as are truly humbled, <hi>for theirs is the Kingdom of God:</hi> ſo alſo ſaith the truth, (yet it is not written) miſerable and curſed are the proud in heart, for theirs is the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Devil; and theſe things are thus found to be truly there where God is man: But where Chriſt and his true followers are, there it is neceſſary, that true, inward, ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual humility and poverty ſhould be, and alſo a dejected and conſtant mind, which mind it is meet ſhould be full of cloſe and hidden calamity and grief, even to the death of the body: And this I do truly avouch, that he that thinketh otherwiſe is deceived, and with himſelf deceiveth others, as hath been ſaid; for this cauſe all nature and ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs doth depart from this kind of life, and doth cleave to the falſe and free life, as hath been ſaid.</p>
               <p>Now ſome <hi>Adam</hi> or Devil, who deſireth to excuſe and defend himſelf, would come upon me, and ſay thus: You would prove in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed that Chriſt was without himſelf, and
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:121281:35"/>many other ſuch like things, yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he ſpeaks often of himſelf, and doth commend himſelf for this and that: Unto which I thus anſwer, When the truth ought, and is willing to do, or will, there is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſe of its will, deſire and action, but that the truth might be known and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted, and this was in Chriſt, and hither did all his works and actions tend, and whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever was moſt profitable and behooful for that, alſo whatſoever things were done by him, from thoſe he was free, as likewiſe from all other things which were done: You will ſay therefore there was in Chriſt ſome cauſe, why he did every thing? Unto which I thus anſwer, If any man ask the Sun why it ſhineth, it would anſwer, it is neceſſary that I ſhine, neither can I do otherwiſe, for this is proper, and belongeth to me, and it is my freedom of nature to be endued with this property, and to ſhine; even ſo it is with God and Chriſt, and all things that are divine, and belonging unto God, that they will do and deſire no other thing, nor no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good, or for good, neither can any other cauſe be alleaged.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:121281:36"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXV.</hi> How all things are to be left or loſt.</head>
               <p>AFter theſe things we muſt obſerve, that it is ſaid, yea, Chriſt himſelf ſaith, that all things are to be left and loſt, which is not to be underſtood, as if men ſhould have nothing, or have to do with nothing; for it is neceſſary that man ſhould have and do even ſomething in this life, wherein he may be employed ſo long as he liveth: But this is thus to be underſtood. Whatſoever any man or creature can do, omit, or know, is not that thing wherein unition or uniting is placed: And what is unition? It is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing but that thy ſelf be plainly, ſingly, and altogether ſimple in the truth, together with the ſimple and eternal will of God: And alſo that thou be wholly voyd of thy own will, and that the created will flow in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the eternal will, and there diſſolve and be turned into nothing, ſo that the ettrnal will do there only will, do, or leave undone any thing. And what is there that can help or further man to this matter? that can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther words, works, nor other Ceremonies do; nor finally any creature, nor the work,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:121281:36"/>power, knowledg, action, or omiſſion of all the creatures.</p>
               <p>Thus ought all things to be loſt and l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ft, which is as much as if you ſhould ſay, it is not to be ſuppoſed or thought that there is any work, ſpeech, knowledg or learning, or any other thing created, which can help, profit in this buſineſs, but all theſe things whatſoever are to be loſt and left, and we muſt make our progreſs unto unition. And yet it is neceſſary that theſe things ſhould be, and ſomething there is which is to be done and left undone, eſpecially a man ought to ſleep and wake, and walk, and ſtand, to ſpeak, and be ſilent, and many other things which muſt needs be, ſo long as a man li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXVI.</hi> That the inner man is unmoveably joyned with God, the outward man notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is moved.</head>
               <p>THis alſo is truly to be obſerved, that where unition befalleth, and is truly made, there immediatly the inner man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth unmoveable, and ſuffereth his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man to be moved hither and thither in
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:121281:37"/>thoſe things, and to thoſe things, which are convenient and neceſſary to be, and come to paſs: So that the outward man may ſay, yea, and ſay truly, I neither will be, nor will not be, neither live, nor dye, neither know, nor be ignorant, neither do, nor leave un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, or whatſoever of this kind, but what is fit and ought to be done, to that I am o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient, whether it be to ſuffer or to act any thing: Thus it comes to paſs, that the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man hath no other cauſe, nor any thing elſe which he ſeeketh, but only to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie the eternal will: for this we may truly perceive, that the inward man ought to ſtand immoveable, and the outward man ought and muſt move. And although the inner man be ſome cauſe of the moving of the outward man, yet this cauſe is no other thing but that it is neceſſary, and muſt be done by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of the eternal will; and where God himſelf would be, or is, there alſo the ſame thing is done, as is to be perceived in Chriſt. Alſo, where this is in the divine, and procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from the divine light, there is not ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual pride, nor fooliſh liberty, or a mind li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centious, but lowly ſubmiſſion, and a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, humbled and ſorrowful ſoul, and all order, juſtice, equality, truth, and whatſoever
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:121281:37"/>belongeth to all vertue: There muſt alſo be peace and contentedneſs of eſtate and condition; but if it be otherwiſe, it is not right with man, as is well elſe-where ſaid more at large: And as truly there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing which may help or further this uniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſo is there nothing which can hinder or avert it, but only man himſelf through his own will.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXVII.</hi> That no man in this life can be free from pain.</head>
               <p>IT is both ſaid and heard, that man ought and may be without pain or grief in this life, as Chriſt was after his Reſurrection. This they go about to confirm out of theſe words of Chriſt: <hi>I will go before you into Galilee, there you ſhall ſee me;</hi> Alſo where he ſaith, <hi>a ſpirit hath neither fleſh nor bones, as ye ſee me have:</hi> which words they would thus expound, As you have ſeen me, and followed me, when I was in a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal body, and in this life, after the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner you ſhall ſee me, and I will go before you, and you ſhall follow me in <hi>Galilee;</hi> that is, you ſhall both feel and taſte, being
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:121281:38"/>painleſs and immutable, in what eſtate you ſhall live, and remain, before you dye the death of the body and ſuffer: And as you ſee me have fleſh and bones, being notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding free from pains, after the ſelf-ſame manner ſhall you be alſo in your corporality and your mortal humanity, not harmed by the death of the body: To this manner of reaſoning it is thus anſwered, Chriſt did not ordain that man ſhould or could attain unto this, except he firſt performed and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered all theſe things which were by Chriſt performed and ſuffered; and if Chriſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained not to this before he firſt endured and ſuffered the death of the body, and all other things that belong thereunto, then ſurely no man can nor ever ſhall attain to this ſo long as he is mortal and ſubject to pain. For if this thing had been the beſt and moſt excellent thing, or if it could or ought to be, that man in this life might attain here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, then ſurely it ſhould firſt have been performed in Chriſt, for the life of Chriſt was and is the beſt, and moſt excellent life; alſo the beſt approved and moſt dear unto God of any that ever was or ſhall be: ſince that this neither ought nor could be done in Chriſt, it ſhall never happen ſurely to
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:121281:38"/>a man in that manner, as to be truly the beſt and moſt excellent: It may be thought and called ſo, but that is no reaſon why it ſhould be ſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXVIII.</hi> How we muſt underſtand, that to a juſt man no law is to be given.</head>
               <p>IT is alſo ſaid, that a man can and may tranſcend all vertue, all Ceremony, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, Commandment, Law and Juſtice, ſo that he may depoſe, ſhake off, and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh all theſe things: here ſomething is true, and ſomething is not true, which muſt be thus conſidered; Chriſt was above the life of Chriſt, and above all Vertue, Ceremony, Ordinance, &amp;c. The Devil alſo is above all thoſe, but after a diverſe manner; Chriſt was and is above all theſe things, if you thus underſtand it; all words, deeds, cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, actions and omiſſions of actions, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, ſpeech, ſuffering, and whatſoever happened to Chriſt, was not neceſſary to him, neither did he ſtand in need of them, neither did they confer any profit at all up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him; and the ſame was and is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of all vertue, ordinances, juſtice, and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:121281:39"/>the like: for whatſoever is, or might be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained unto by theſe things, all that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in Chriſt, and there in readineſs; and if you thus underſtand the caſe, then it is true; in the ſame ſenſe, that ſaying of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> is true and ſo to be underſtood, Thoſe who are endued, carryed, and lead by the Spirit of God, are the ſons of God, and not ſubject to the Law; the ſenſe of which words is this, they are not to be taught what they ſhould do or leave undone, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Spirit of God, which is their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructer, will teach them ſufficiently, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is any thing to be commanded or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned them, as to do good, to ſhun evil, or the like; for he that teacheth them what is good, or not good, beſt, or not beſt; the ſame, I ſay, doth command and enjoyn them, likewiſe to retain the beſt, and quit the contrary, and they obey him according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Hereupon it is that they need look for no Law, Doctrine, or precept; for another reaſon alſo they need no law, by means whereof to obtain or get profit to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; for whatſoever might be obtained, or gotten by theſe things, or by the help of all the creatures, or by ſpeech, words, or works, either in eternal life, or to eternal
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:121281:39"/>life, all that they have obtained already; If you underſtand the cauſe on this manner, it is true, that a man may become more higher and excellent then all law and vertue, and alſo then the works, and knowledg, and ſtrength of all creatures; But if you affirm that other, which is, that both ought to be done, I mean, that both the life of Chriſt, as alſo all commandments, laws, ordinances, and the like, ought to be layd aſide, and caſt off, and to be neglected, contemned and derided, then is it falſe, and full of lyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIX.</hi> Of the true and falſe Lights, and of perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance in the life of Chriſt.</head>
               <p>NOw ſome will ſay, If neither Chriſt, nor any other man, can obtain any thing, nor reap any profit by the life of Chriſt, nor by all Ceremonies, and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, &amp;c. for whatſoever may be obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by thoſe things that they have already, what further cauſe is there why they ſhould not leave off to do theſe things? or why ought they to uſe theſe things afterwards, or handle or have them any longer in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count?</p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:121281:40"/>
               <p>This is to be obſerved, that there are two Lights, the one a true, the other a falſe light; the true light is the eternal Light, which is God; or elſe it is a created Light, which is notwithſtanding Divine, and is called Grace, and this is the true Light: The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is a falſe Light, which is the Light of Nature, or natural light: But why the firſt light ſhould be true, and the other falſe, it may be better obſerved then either written or ſpoken: Nothing appertaineth to God, as to the Divinity; neither will, nor know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, nor ſatisfaction, nor any thing at all that can be named, ſpoken, or thought; but to God, as God, it appertaineth, that he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay himſelf open, know and love himſelf, that he manifeſt himſelf to himſelf in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; and all this is God; and that he is an offence and not an action, as being without the creature: And in this opening, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation, is the diſtinction of perſons. But where God, as God, is man, or where God liveth in ſome Divine or Deified man, there is ſomething belonging unto God, which is only appertaining to him, and not to the creatures; and God is that in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, without the creature, originally or eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentially, not in form or action: and yet
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:121281:40"/>God would have this ſame to be put in practice; for therefore it is, that it might be conferred to action, and ſo exerciſed: for what then ſhould it be? ſhould it be idle, what then ſhould it profit? for that which is of no uſe is not at all: Now this neither God nor Nature would have; But if God would have this exerciſed and brought into action, and that this cannot be done without the creature, it is then ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that it be ſo done: What then? If it were neither this nor that, nor if it were neither any work nor action, or the like, what ſhould it be? or what ſhould God himſelf become to be? or what ſhould he himſelf be? Here you muſt return and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide, leſt, by crawling (as it were) ſo far, you be brought to that paſs at the laſt, as not to know which way to turn, or by what means to creep back again.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXX.</hi> That God is one and ſimple good, and only to be loved.</head>
               <p>NOw this is to be obſerved; God, as he is God, is good and goodneſs it ſelf, and is neither this good, nor that good;
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:121281:41"/>but here ſomething is to be marked, which is ſomewhere, either here or there, and that is, not in all ends, nor above all ends or places. Alſo that which is ſometimes to day, or to morrow, is not always, nor every time, nor above all times; and that which is ſomething, either this or that, is not all things, nor above all things. Now under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand this after this manner: If God were any thing, either this, or that, he were not all things, nor above all things, as he is, and ſo ſhould not be the true perfection; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he is God, and yet is not this nor that, which the creatures, as they aye creatures, are able to know, name, think, or utter; therefore if God, as he is good, were this good or that good, he ſhould not be all good, neither ſhould he be the ſimple and perfect good, which notwithſtanding he is. Now if God be alſo light and knowledg, it appertaineth to light and knowledg, and is proper to it, to be bright and to ſhine, to appear and know. And becauſe God is light and knowledg, it is neceſſary that he ſhine, be bright, and endued with know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg; and all this, to ſhine and know, is in God, without the creatures, becauſe he is not here as an action, but an eſſence and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:121281:41"/>And that it ſhould be done as an action, by doing, it is neceſſary that it ſhould be done in the creatures: And therefore when this knowledg and light doth work in any creature, there it doth know and learn what it ſelf is, and ſo it is good, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is not this or that; and further, it doth not know this or that, but it doth know and learn to know, that one, true, ſimple, perfect good, which is neither this nor that, but is all good, and above all good.</p>
               <p>Now it is here ſaid, that he muſt learn that only good: but doth any man learn of himſelf? obſerve and mark this well, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as God is good, knowledg and light, ſo is he alſo will, love, juſtice and truth; he is alſo all vertue, and yet theſe are all one eſſence in God; neither can any of theſe be brought into action or exerciſe without the creature, for in God there is nothing but eſſence and beginning, not any action: But when this <hi>one</hi> (which notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is all theſe) ſhall gain any creature un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it ſelf, and hath power over it, and doth ſo prepare it and fit it, that it may know in it what belongeth to it ſelf; ſo far forth (I ſay) as that <hi>one</hi> is will and love, and is taught of it ſelf, as it is light and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:121281:42"/>knowledg, neither willeth any thing, but that <hi>one</hi> which is it ſelf. And furthermore, here is nothing willed or eſteemed, but that which is good as it is good, and that for no other reaſon, but becauſe it is good, and not by reaſon it is this or that, beloved of this man or that man, and either pleaſant or grievous to this man or that man, ſweet or bitter, and the like; and theſe things are not regarded nor ſought, either for ſelf, or as it ſelf: alſo all ſelfneſs and egoity, I, and to me, &amp;c. are here left and fall to the ground; ſo that it is not ſaid, I love my ſelf, or thee, or the like; and if love were asked what it loveth, it would anſwer, I love God; and why? becauſe it is good and for good, therefore it is meet and right that it ſhould be moſt eſteemed; and if there were any thing better then God, That were and ought to be loved for God: Therefore God doth not love himſelf, as himſelf, but as good; and if God knew any thing bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then God, he would love that and not himſelf; ſo far is God from all egoity and ſelfneſs; neither hath he any thing to do with it further then is needful, in reſpect of the perſons: and this both ought to be, and in truth is, in a divine and truly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ words">
                     <desc>〈◊…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:121281:42"/>otherwiſe that man were neither divine nor deified.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXI.</hi> That a deified man knows nothing but to love.</head>
               <p>HEnce it cometh, that a deified man is indeed indued with pure and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingled love, and is kind and loving to all men, and all things; and therefore it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that he ſhould love all men, and all things, and that he ſhould wiſh well to all men and all things; and that he ſhould ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor and do them any good, without put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting any difference: Beſides, whatſoever you do to a deified man, whether it be pleaſant, or troubleſome, amiable, or grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous, or whatſoever it is; yea, I will fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſay, although a man ſhould kill ſuch a one, and he ſhould ſo often return to life, he would notwithſtanding heartily love that man who had ſo often ſlain him; and although he had done him ſo many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries, as you can deviſe, yet he would not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding from his heart wiſh him well, reſpect him, and deſire all good to befall him, yea and perform all good offices to
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:121281:43"/>him, ſo as the other were able to accept and admit them. This may be obſerved and plainly proved in Chriſt, who ſaid unto <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das,</hi> that betrayed him, <hi>Friend, Wherefore art thou come?</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, Thou hateſt me, and art mine enemy; whereas I love thee, and am thy friend; and thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireſt, and wiſheſt, and doſt what evil to me thou either knoweſt or canſt; whereas I both deſire, and wiſh, and will well unto thee, and would give, and do unto thee willingly, all things that be good, if thou wert able to take and receive them: As if God ſhould ſay out of his humanity, I am the pure and ſimple good, and therefore I neither can, will, deſire, wiſh, do, or give any thing but good. And if I muſt reward thee for thy wickedneſs and ungodlineſs, I muſt do it with good, ſeeing I am nothing elſe, nor have any thing elſe. Hence it is that God in a deified man deſires no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, nor doth will or do any miſchief, wherewith he is or may be affected; this may be ſeen in Chriſt, who ſaid, <hi>Father, forgive them, for they know not what they do.</hi> This alſo is proper to God, that he compelleth no man to do, or omit any thing, but ſuffereth every man according to his
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:121281:43"/>own mind to do, or leave undone as wel good as evil things. Neither will he reſiſt any man; this we may ſee in Chriſt who would not reſiſt his malefactors And again, when Saint <hi>Peter</hi> would have made reſiſtance, he ſaid, <hi>Peter put up thy ſword into thy ſcab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard,</hi> for it is neither my cuſtom nor yours, who belong to me, to reſiſt by force, ſtrive, or compel: Neither yet can a deified man vex or grieve any man, which is thus to be underſtood; It never falleth into his will, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, or mind, to do or leave undone anything, to ſpeak or to be ſilent, whereby he might breed pain or grief to any man.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXII.</hi> That the will of man is prone to evil, and therefore to be forſaken.</head>
               <p>SOme man will ſay, If he willeth, wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and doth the beſt, unto every man, he ought alſo to help every man, and cauſe all things to befall him according to his hearts deſire. For example, ſo as one might obtain to be made Pope, another a Biſhop, &amp;c. I anſwer, he that furthereth the will of man, helpeth him to the worſt
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:121281:44"/>things; for the more that man followeth his own will, and increaſeth in the ſame, ſo much the further he is from God and the true good.</p>
               <p>Now God would willingly help man, and bring him to that which is beſt, and of it ſelf the beſt for man; but that this ſhould come to paſs, it is neceſſary that all ſelf-will ſhould ceaſe, (as before hath been ſaid,) and thus God would willingly help man; but as long as man doth ſeek that which is beſt for himſelf, he doth not ſeek that which ſhould be beſt for him, and therefore he never findeth it; for it both is and were beſt for man, neither to ſeek nor embrace himſelf, nor that which is his, which God both teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and ſaith. If then, any man deſire to be helped by God, to that which both in it ſelf is beſt, and alſo beſt for man, let him follow the ſayings, Doctrines and Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandments of God, ſo ſhall he receive help, &amp; ſo is he now helped; there is no other means: Now God teacheth, and ſaith, That man ought to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake himſelf, and all that he hath, and follow him; for whoſoever loveth his own ſoul, that is, himſelf, and will be ſaved and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended; <hi>id eſt,</hi> he who hath a care of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and his own, in theſe matters, he ſhall
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:121281:44"/>loſe his ſoul; but he who regardeth not his ſoul, and loſeth both himſelf and all things belonging to him, he ſhall ſave his ſoul, and preſerve it to eternal life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXIII.</hi> Of true humility, and ſpiritual poverty.</head>
               <p>ANd now that which is proper unto God in a deified man, is, a true inward and ſincere humility, and where that is not, there is not a deified man, this Chriſt both taught in his Word, and Works, and Life; and hence proceeded this humility, becauſe ſuch a man perceiveth by the true light, that which indeed every thing is, and that to be, to live, to know, to be able, and the like, do belong only to the true God, and not to the creatures. For a creature, as it is a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is nothing and hath nothing of it ſelf; and as ſoon as it turneth it ſelf aſide from the true God, by its own will, works, &amp;c. there is nothing but unrighteouſneſs found in it; and therefore this alſo is very truth indeed, that a creature, as it is a creature of it ſelf, is worthy of nothing, and hath right <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> nothing, neither doth any ow it any thing, either God or the creature; but by
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:121281:45"/>right it ought to obey and be ſubject to God. And this is the chiefeſt matter, and eſpecially to be regarded; therefore that which ought and will be obedient and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject unto God, ought alſo, and muſt be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to all creatures, and that, as I may brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpeak, not in action, but in ſufferings, or elſe it is falſe; and from this laſt matter, and from this laſt ſentence, proceedeth true humility, which if it were not truly ſo, and if this true and Divine Juſtice were not the beſt things, Chriſt would never have ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther taught it by his Word, or performed it by his Life. And in this conſiſteth true confeſſion, and is true after this manner, that the creatures ought in regard of divine grace, and for juſtice ſake, become ſubject to God, and all creatures, and nothing ought to be ſubject or to obey the creature it ſelf; yea, all the creatures have right and claim againſt it, and unto it; whereas it ſelf hath right to nothing, or againſt any thing, and is indebted to all, nothing being indebted to it, and this by ſuffering, and ſometimes alſo by doing: And from hence ariſeth ſpiritual poverty, of which Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Bleſſed are the poor in ſpirit, for theirs is, the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> All theſe things
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:121281:45"/>Chriſt taught in words, and practiſed in life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXIV.</hi> That ſin only is contrary to God.</head>
               <p>BUT here ſomething is to be obſerved: It is ſaid that ſomething is, and may be done againſt God, and that there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what which doth grieve him, and make him ſorrowful: we muſt know that there is no creature againſt God, or which can procure his grief or ſorrow, in that it is, or in that it liveth, knoweth, or can do any things, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever are of this kind, are not contrary to God: That the Devil or man liveth, is, and the like, all this is good, and proceeds from God, for God is every way all theſe things, eſſentially and originally.</p>
               <p>God, I ſay, is the eſſence of all things which are the life of every thing that liveth, and the wiſdom of all that are wiſe, for all things have their being, their power, their life, and more truly in God then in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, otherwiſe God were not all good, and therefore all things are abſolutely good.</p>
               <p>Now that which is good; is beloved of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:121281:46"/>God, and he will have it; and therefore it is not contrary to him. What then is grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous and contrary to God? nothing but ſin: and what is ſin? no other thing but that the creature willeth otherwiſe then God willeth, yea, contrary to the will of God: Every man may perceive this in himſelf, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this manner, he that willeth otherwiſe then I do, or contrary to that which I do, he is mine enemy; and he that willeth the ſame that I do, he is my friend, and dear unto me: After the ſame manner it is with God; You have here what ſin is, and what is contrary to God, and what doth grieve and make him ſorrowful; he therefore that willeth otherwiſe then I do, or contrary to that which I do, whatſoever he doth, or leaveth undone, whether he ſpeak or hold his peace, all that is contrary and grievous unto me: and ſo in like manner it is with God, he that willeth otherwiſe, or contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to God, whatſoever he doth, or doth not, or whatſoever he taketh in hand, is contrary to God, and is ſin; and whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver willeth otherwiſe then God, the ſame is contrary to the will of God: For Chriſt ſaith, <hi>He that is not with me, is againſt me:</hi> the meaning whereof is this; he that will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:121281:46"/>not the ſame thing, and is not of the ſame mind with me, he is of a will contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to me. By theſe things a man may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive whether he doth commit ſin or no, and what ſin is; by what means, or after what manner, ſin may or ought to be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected or amended. And this is that will which is ſaid to be contrary to God, and it is termed Diſobedience, <hi>Adam,</hi> Egoity, and Selfneſs, our own will, ſin, the old man, to turn from God, and to ſeparate our ſelves from him; all theſe are one and the ſame thing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXV.</hi> That God in himſelf is impatiable, in man he is patiable.</head>
               <p>NOw this is to be obſerved; That pain, trouble, and diſpleaſure, doth not fall upon God, as he is God; and yet God is troubled for the ſin of man. And becauſe this cannot come to paſs in God without the creature, it is neceſſary that it be done where God is man, <hi>id eſt,</hi> in a deified man. But here ſin bringeth ſo great ſorrow and grief unto God, that God would will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly be tormented, and endure corporal
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:121281:47"/>death; ſo as by that means he might but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh the ſin of one man: And if it ſhould be demanded whether God had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther live, ſin remaining, or not to deſtroy ſin by his death, he would anſwer, that he would rather dye; for the ſin of one man is more grievous to God, and troubleth him more then the torment and death of God himſelf. Then if the ſin of one man grieve him ſo much, what grief ſhall we think that he undergoeth through the ſins of men in general? Here we may perceive after what manner man troubleth God by ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and where God is man, or in a deified man, there is no complaint of any thing but of ſin, neither doth any thing elſe cauſe grief; for whatſoever is, or is done without ſin, that God would have, and that ſhould be. But the complaint of ſorrow which is for ſin, that is meet and fitting that it ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in a deified man until the death of the body, though he ſhould live to the laſt day, and for ever. From hence did and doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe the hidden ſorrow of Chriſt, which no man can either utter or know, but only Chriſt, and therefore it is both called, and indeed is a hidden ſorrow. And ſurely this is a thing proper to God, who will have it
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:121281:47"/>ſo, and delighted therewith in man, and is certainly appertaining to God, for it doth not belong to man, neither is it in mans power, and where God can attain to this, he holdeth it moſt dear and acceptable to him, but to man it is moſt bitter and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous. All things which are here ſet down of the propriety of God which he will have in man, in whom they are erected and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, this, I ſay, the true light teacheth, and it doth therefore teach that man (upon whom it is beſtowed, and in whom it is exerciſed to this end) might no more challenge it as his own, then if himſelf were not at all: for by this means at the length it doth appear that man is not able to do this, neither ought it to be attributed to him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXVI,</hi> That the life of Chriſt is to be loved for it ſelf, and not for reward.</head>
               <p>THerefore, whereſoever ſuch a kind of deified man ſhould be, or is, there alſo may be, and is, the beſt and excellenteſt life, and moſt acceptable unto God of any that ever was or ſhall be hereafter: and out of the eternal love, which loveth God, as good,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:121281:48"/>and for good, and doth alſo love that in all things which is beſt and moſt excellent, only for good; this true and worthy life is ſo much beloved, that it is never forſaken of that man in whom it is, although he ſhould live even to the laſt day; yea, and further, it is unpoſſible that it ſhould be forſaken, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though that man ſhould dye a thouſand deaths, and all evils ſhould befall him which can befall all creatures, he would, I ſay, be more willing to endure all theſe things then forſake this excellent life, although he could, in exchange thereof, obtain the life of an Angel: And here anſwer is made to the queſtion, Where it is asked, if a man by a Chriſtian life obtain nothing more, nor can raiſe any other profit, what need is there then that he ſhould do any thing?</p>
               <p>This life is not followed to this end, that thence profit ought to ariſe, or any other thing be gained, but only in the behalf of love, and the excellency thereof alſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is dear and acceptable to God: Now if any man will ſay, or think, that he hath gotten enough of it, or that he may give it over, this man doth neither feel nor know it; for where it is truly found and felt, it can never be forſaken; but he that hath the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:121281:48"/>life of Chriſt to this end, that thereby he may attain or deſerve ſomething, this man hath it as an hireling and not for love, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he hath it not at all: He that hath it not in love, hath it not; and although he thinks he have it, he is deceived: Chriſt had this life, not for reward, but for love; and love makes this life eaſie, and not grievous, cauſing it to paſs away cheerfuly, and to be willingly born. But he that doth not keep it for love, but ſuppoſeth that he hath it for reward, to him it is moſt grievous, and he deſires to be ſoon rid of it; and this is the property of every hireling, to deſire and wiſh an end of his labor: whereas a true lover taketh neither pain, time, nor labor, in ill part: for this cauſe it is written, To ſerve God, and to live to him, is eaſie to him that doth it; this indeed is true, to him that doth all things in love; but to him that doth them for reward, it is grievous: the ſame is to be held of all vertues and good deeds, and alſo of integrity, equity, and the like.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXVII.</hi> That God is above all order.</head>
               <p>IT is ſaid, and it is true, that God is above all cuſtom, meaſure, and order, and giveth
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:121281:49"/>cuſtom, order, and meaſure to all things; which muſt be thus underſtood: God is willing to have all theſe things, but not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding he cannot have them in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf without the creature; for in God, without the creature, there is neither order nor confuſion, Rite nor Ceremony; for this cauſe his will is, that theſe things ſhould be, and that they may and ought to be done; for where word, work, or action is, there is neceſſity that theſe ſhould be done, either according to order, cuſtom, meaſure, or reaſon, or without order.</p>
               <p>Now order and reaſon are better and more excellent then theſe things which are contrary to them.</p>
               <p>But now we muſt obſerve, that there are four ſorts of men who do hold Order, Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony and Law.</p>
               <p>Some do it neither for God, nor for any other cauſe, but only by compulſion; and theſe indeed do it as little as they can, and that which they do is bitter and grievous to them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Others do it for reward; theſe are they who know no other thing but the ſame, and do, that men may and ought to obtain and deſerve the Kingdom of God and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:121281:49"/>life after this manner, and by no other means; and that he, who performeth the moſt of theſe things, is bleſſed; and he that doth omit or neglect any of them, is dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and belongeth to the Devil: and theſe men uſe great pains and diligence herein, yet it is a bitter thing unto them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The third ſort are evil and falſe ſpirits, who think and ſay that they are perfect, and that they ſtand in no need of theſe things, and therefore hold them in ſcorn and deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</p>
               <p n="4">4. The fourth ſort are ſuch who are filled with a true light, and do not theſe things for reward, for they deſire not to obtain any thing by them, or to attain any thing by their help: But whatſoever thing they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, concerning theſe, they do it out of love: And theſe men are not ſo careful, how many of theſe things, or how ſoon they do theſe or the like things; but how well, and that they may be done in peace and meaſure: And if by chance it happen, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of theſe, or the like, be neglected, they do not therefore fall into deſpair, for they know very wel, that order &amp; reaſon are better, and of more eſteem then any thing that is done without reaſon, therefore they will obſerve
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:121281:50"/>order, and yet they know that happyneſs is not placed therein, and therefore they are not ſo much troubled as others are, and they are blamed &amp; contemned of all other Sects: For the hirelings ſay, theſe men do altogether neglect themſelves, and ſometimes they ſay, that they are wicked, and the like: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who are of a free ſpirit, ſay in a ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing manner, that they behave themſelves fooliſhly, blockiſhly, and the like: But they themſelves do hold that which is mean and the beſt; for one lover of God is better and dearer to God then a hundred thouſand hirelings, and we ought to hold the like opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of their works.</p>
               <p>This alſo is to be obſerved, that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment; Speech, and all the Doctrine of God do tend to this purpoſe, that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man may be joyned to God, which when it comes to paſs, the outward man is ſo well ordered and inſtructed by the inner man, that indeed he ſtandeth not in need of any outward Precept or Doctrine; but the Precepts and Laws of men belong to the outward man, and are neceſſary where bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things are unknown; for theſe men are ignorant, either what to do, or what to leave undone; ſo as if Diſcipline be wanting,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:121281:50"/>men become like to dogs, and other beaſts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXVIII.</hi> The deſcription of falſe light.</head>
               <p>HAving made mention of a falſe light, ſomething muſt be ſpoken thereof, as what it is, and what properly belongeth to it: Know therefore, that whatſoever is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the true light, is belonging to the falſe. It is a general property of the true light not to deceive, nor to will that any ſhould be deceived, neither to be deceived it ſelf: But the falſe light doth deceive, and is deceived: for God will deceive no man, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can he be willing that any man ſhould be deceived: and ſo may you judg alſo of the true light. Now mark this, the true light is God, and ſome divine thing: The falſe light is men, or ſome natural thing. Now it is proper to God, not to be this or that, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to will, deſire, or ſeek this or that in a deified man, but good as good, and that for no other thing but for good: the ſame is to be held of the true light.</p>
               <p>Alſo, it is proper to the creature and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to be ſomething, this or that, and to hold ſomething in eſtimation, and to deſire
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:121281:51"/>it, either this or that; neither doth it love that which is meerly good, as good, and for good, but for ſome other thing, this or that. And even as God, and the true light, is void of all egoity, ſelfneſs, and ſeeking it ſelf; ſo the property and nature of the natural falſe light, is, to be I, my ſelf, me, &amp;c. ſo as it ſeeks it ſelf, and its own in all things, more then good, as it is good; this is proper to it, and the nature of every each one.</p>
               <p>Now let this be obſerved, whereſoever this light is, at the firſt, deceived, it doth not will nor chooſe any good, as good, and for good, but it willeth and chooſeth it ſelf, and its own, as the beſt, which is falſhood, and the firſt deceiving. It doth alſo ſuppoſe, that it is that which it is not; for it doth ſuppoſe it ſelf to be God, being nothing but nature, and ſuppoſing it ſelf to be God, it challengeth to it ſelf that which is proper to God, and not that which belongeth to God, as God is man, or as he is ſome deified man, but it challengeth to it ſelf that which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to God, and is proper to him, as he is God, and without the creature for ever and ever: For (as it is ſaid before) God is not poor, neither wanteth he any thing, he is free without buſineſs, at liberty above all
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:121281:51"/>things, &amp;c. All which are true, he is alſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable, neither doth he challenge any thing to himſelf, he is without Religion, and whatſoever he doth, is juſt: After the ſame manner, (ſaith the falſe light) will I alſo be, for the liker any one is to God, ſo much is he alſo the better, wherefore it ſaith, <hi>I will be like unto God, nay I will be God, and ſit neer God, I will, I ſay, be like unto him, as Lucifer the Devil did.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God is everlaſtingly without pain, paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and trouble, ſo that nothing is or can be done, which is grievous to him, or can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure his pain; but where God is man, or in any deified man, the matter is far other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Whatſoever can be deceived, is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by this falſe light: And ſeeing what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is not God or Divine, may be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: and ſince that this light is nature it ſelf, it cometh to paſs that it may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, therefore it is deceived, and alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of it ſelf.</p>
               <p>Some will ſay, how cometh it to paſs, that whatſoever can be deceived, is deceived of it ſelf? This doth proceed from the great and unmeaſurable craftineſs thereof; for it is ſo ſubtile, deceitful, and nimble of it
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:121281:52"/>ſelf, that it aſcendeth and climbeth ſo high, as to ſuppoſe it ſelf to be above men, that neither nature, or any creature, can poſſibly mount ſo high; for this cauſe it ſuppoſeth it ſelf to be God; then therefore it doth ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate to it ſelf all things which belong to God, and eſpecially as God is in eternity, and not as God is man: For this cauſe it thinketh it ſelf to be above all word, work, cuſtom, order, and even above the corporal Life of Chriſt, which he did lead in his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity; and therefore it refuſeth to be touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of any creature, or the works of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, whether they be good or evil, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be againſt God, or otherwiſe; all theſe it accounteth alike, and will be freed from them, as if it were the eternal God. But all other things which are belonging to God, and to no creature, it doth arrogate to it ſelf, as if it were worthy of all things, and as if it were meet and right that all the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſhould ſerve and be ſubject unto it.</p>
               <p>Thus it comes to paſs, that there remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth neither ſorrow, paſſions, nor troubles for any other thing or cauſe, but only the feeling of the body and ſences, which muſt remain until the death of the body, and whatſoever pain can ariſe from thence: Yea, it doth ſay and <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:121281:52"/>ſuppoſe, that man is become higher then the corporal life of Chriſt, and that he is and ought to be without pain and untouched, as Chriſt was after his Reſurrection.</p>
               <p>There are many other, and wonderful er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, which do ariſe and proceed hence. Seeing then that this falſe light is nature, it hath the ſame property that nature hath, that is, to admire and ſeek it ſelf, and its own, in all things; and that which is the beſt and fitteſt, moſt pleaſant and ſweet to nature it ſelf in all things; and becauſe it is deceived, it doth think and ſay, that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is the beſt, ſweeteſt and moſt fit for it ſelf, that indeed is the beſt of all other things, and it doth ſay, that 'tis the beſt of all that every man ſhould ſeek, do and will that which is beſt for himſelf: it knows none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good but its own, and that which is beſt for it ſelf, as it ſuppoſeth: But if you ſpeak unto it of the true and ſimple good, which is neither this nor that, it knows not what it is, but only laugheth it to ſcorn, which indeed is fitting to be ſo; for nature, as it is nature, cannot attain to it: Therefore ſeeing this light is mearly nature, it cannot proceed ſo far.</p>
               <p>This falſe light doth alſo ſay, that it hath
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:121281:53"/>ſurmounted both Religion and Conſcience, and whatſoever it doth, is right: In ſo much that a certain falſe libertine ſpirit did ſay, ſtanding in this error, that although he had ſlain ten thouſand men, he would make no more conſcience of it then if he had killed a dog.</p>
               <p>Briefly, this falſe and deceived light doth fly all things that are contrary and grievous to nature, and this is proper unto it, becauſe it is nature: and being ſo deceived, as that it ſuppoſeth it ſelf to be God, it doubted not to ſwear, by all the Saints, that it knoweth the thing which is the beſt, and hath his exiſtence in it, ſo that it intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth only to extol and ſeek that which is the beſt of all.</p>
               <p>Thus it cometh to paſs, that it never either is amended or taught more then the Devil himſelf.</p>
               <p>Obſerve alſo, that this light doth ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it ſelf to be God, and arrogateth the ſame to it ſelf, and herein it is <hi>Lucifer,</hi> the Devil: and whereas it doth reject the Life of Chriſt, and many other things belonging to the true good, and ſuch as were taught &amp; beloved of Chriſt, it is Antichriſt, ſeeing it doth teach and live againſt and contrary to
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:121281:53"/>Chriſt: And even as this light is deceived by its own ſubtilty, ſo likewiſe are all things deceived by it, which are neither God nor Divine; that is, all men who are not illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated with the true light, and the love thereof: for whoſoever they are that are illuminated of the true light they are never deceived; but whoſoever hath it not, and yet is ſo affected, as that he will walk with this falſe light, and remain in it, he is decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: And this comes to paſs, becauſe all men that are in the light (which is not true) are turned into themſelves, and do eſteem themſelves, and that which is profitable, and fit for them, to be the chiefeſt good; and if any man will commend and propound that unto them for the chiefeſt good, and will help them to it, and teach them how to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it, him they follow and eſteem as their Maſter.</p>
               <p>Now this falſe light doth teach all things belonging thereunto, and therefore all men follow it, who know not the true light; ſo it comes to paſs, that they are deceived both together.</p>
               <p>It is ſaid of Antichriſt, that when he cometh, all that have not the Seal of God ſhall follow him, thoſe which have it ſhall
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:121281:54"/>not follow him; and that is the ſame light: this is true indeed; if any man can attain to that which is beſt for himſelf, <hi>viz.</hi> that which is beſt, to God ward, that is excellent; but this is not done ſo long as man ſeeketh and loveth that which is beſt for himſelf; For to the end he may find and obtain that which is beſt for himſelf; it is neceſſary that he firſt loſe that whith is beſt for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as hath been already ſaid: But if a man be willing to forſake and loſe that which is beſt for himſelf, to the end he may find that which is beſt for himſelf, this again is falſe; therefore there are but few that can come into this way.</p>
               <p>This falſe light, that a man ought to be voyd of Religion, and that he is a fool and a block, who maketh any account thereof, and this it would prove from Chriſt, who was voyd of Religion; to the which an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer is made, that the Devil is voyd alſo of Religion, yet he is no whit the better for being ſo.</p>
               <p>Underſtand therefore what Religion is; —Religion is when it is acknowledged that man is averſe or diverted from God by his own will (which both is truly named and called ſin) and that this was mans fault, and
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:121281:54"/>not Gods; for God is free from all fault of ſinning; who is he therefore that knoweth himſelf to be guiltleſs, except Chriſt alone (and ſome few beſides.) Know, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is voyd of Religion, is either Chriſt or the Devil: In a word, whereſoever the true light is, there is alſo a true and upright life which is acceptable and beloved of God: And although it be not the Life of Chriſt in perfection, yet notwithſtanding it is rectifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and framed to the imitation of him, and ſuch a one loveth the Life of Chriſt, and whatſoever properly belongeth to reaſon, order, and all vertues: In this life, I ſay, all ſelfneſs, I, mine, &amp;c. periſheth.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Nothing is in it admired or ſought, but only good for good, and as it is good. But where the falſe light is, there is no regard had, either of Chriſt or all ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, but that is ſought and beloved, which is fitting and pleaſing to nature: hence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth falſe and inordinate liberties, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by man becometh ſecure and negligent in, and of every thing: For the true light is the ſeed of God, and therefore brings forth the fruit of God: The falſe light is the ſeed of the Devil, and where it is ſown, there alſo the fruit of the Devil and the Devil
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:121281:55"/>himſelf increaſeth: This may be perceived and underſtood by the words and argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments formerly ſet down.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXIX.</hi> Who and what a deified man is.</head>
               <p>IT might be demanded who is, or what is a deified, or a divine man? whereunto I anſwer; he who is illuminated and enbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with divine light, and kindled with the eternal and divine love, is a divine and a deified man: And of this light we have made ſome mention heretofore. But we muſt know, that light and knowledg is fit for nothing, nor is nothing without love; which may here be perceived; that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though a man very well know what vertue or vice is, yet except he love vertue, he becometh not, neither is endued with ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, but leaving vertue he followeth vice: But if he embrace vertue, then he followeth it; and this love cauſeth himſelf to become an enemy to vice, and in ſuch manner, that he cannot only not entertain nor commit ſin, but alſo maketh him to hate it in all men, yea, he doth ſo far love vertue, that he
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:121281:55"/>cannot be at reſt, except he doth exerciſe or enjoy it as much as he may, and that for no other cauſe, but for that he loveth vertue, and vertue it ſelf is a reward to him, with enjoying of which he reſts ſo well content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as that he will not exchange her for any treaſure.</p>
               <p>This is he who becometh and is a vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man, and he that is truly endued with vertue, would not for the whole world be bereaved of vertue: Nay, he had rather dye a miſerable death.</p>
               <p>We may ſpeak the like of Juſtice; moſt men know ſufficiently what is juſtice, yet do they not become juſt, for they love not juſtice, and therefore they exerciſe vice and injuſtice, for if they loved juſtice, they could do nothing which were unjuſt, for they would hate and become ſuch enemies to injuſtice, as that if they ſhould perceive it in any man, they would willingly ſuffer and act great matters, whereby injuſtice might he rooted out, and man become juſt, and had rather dye then do any unjuſt thing, and all theſe they would do for no other cauſe nor end, but the love of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and juſtice ſhould be their reward, and ſufficiently recompence them. Such a
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:121281:56"/>one becometh, and is a juſt man, who had rather dye an hundred times then live un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly.</p>
               <p>The like may be ſaid of truth; Although a man know, in many things, what is true, what is falſe, and a lye, yet if he love not the truth, he is not a true man; and if he do love it, then that befalleth him which is ſaid of juſtice. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaketh of juſtice when he ſaith, <hi>Wo to them that are of a double ſpirit:</hi> thoſe are they who outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſerve God, but inwardly are full of lyes, in whoſe mouth a lye is found.</p>
               <p>Hence we may learn, that knowledg and skill, being voyd of love, is of no moment. The like is alſo underſtood of the devil, who knoweth and underſtandeth evil and good, juſt and unjuſt, truth and falſhood, &amp;c. But becauſe he loveth not the good, which he knoweth, he becometh not good, which ſurely he would, if he could love the truth, and other good things and vertues, which he knoweth: It is true indeed, that love and knowledg ought to be taught, but if love do not follow knowledg and accompany it, nothing is gained.</p>
               <p>And ſuch is the conſideration of God, and of his nature, and of thoſe things that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertain
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:121281:56"/>to him, that if any man have great knowledg of God, and of his nature, and thinketh that he knoweth and underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth what God is, except he be endued with love, he cannot become divine or deified: But if he hath true love, it is certain that ſuch a man doth cleave unto God, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaketh all ſuch things as are not God, nor appertaining to God, and that he doth hate, and is at enmity with all ſuch things, not enduring them, being grievous to him; and this love doth ſo joyn a man to God, that he can never be ſeparated from him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XL.</hi> Whether God may be known, and yet not loved.</head>
               <p>HEnce a queſtion ariſeth, becauſe it is ſaid, he that knoweth God not, and loveth him not, can never be bleſſed. From this kind of knowledg there ariſeth, what kind of knowledg that is whereby God may be known, and yet not loved, ſeeing it is ſaid elſwheres, that where God is known, he there alſo is loved; and that he that doth know God, doth alſo neceſſarily love him: how then can theſe contrary ſayings agree
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:121281:57"/>together? unto which I anſwer, that here again ſomething is to be obſerved: We have formerly ſpoken of two lights, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the one is true, and the other falſe; after the ſame manner we muſt diſcern that there is a double love, a true one, and a falſe one, both which muſt be taught and brought un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us by ſome light or knowledg: Now the true light worketh true love, and the falſe light falſe love, for that which the falſe light doth account to be beſt, the ſame it doth propound and perſwade to be loved as the beſt, and love doth follow and obey what it commandeth. Now it is formerly taught, that the falſe light is natural and nature, ſo as whatſoever is proper and belonging to nature, is proper and belonging to it, as I, mine, to me, this, that, this mans, &amp;c. It is neceſſary therefore it ſhould be deceived, and falſe in it ſelf, for I, or mine, never comes to the true light or knowledg undeceived, except only one, which is the divine perſons. And to the end we may come to the knowledg of the ſimple truth, it is neceſſary that all theſe periſh. This alſo is one ſpecial property belonging to the natural falſe light, that it deſireth to know all things, if it be poſſible; and conceiveth
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:121281:57"/>much joy and pleaſure, boaſting in its know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg and learning, deſiring always to know more &amp; more, and yet never reſteth, or is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented therewithall; and the more or higher things that it knoweth, the greater occaſion it taketh of joy and boaſting; and when it is come to ſo great heighth, that it ſuppoſeth it ſelf to know all things, and more then all, then is it in the higheſt pleaſure and trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phing, accounting of that knowledg as the moſt beſt &amp; excellent thing, and therefore it teacheth, that knowledg and learning ought to be loved, as the moſt beſt and excellent thing. And thus it comes to paſs, that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg &amp; learning is more eſteemed of then the thing it ſelf which is known; for the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and falſe light doth better love its know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg and learning (<hi>id eſt,</hi> it ſelf) then that ſelf-ſame thing which is known, as if it were poſſible that the ſame natural light could know God, and the ſimple truth, as it is in God and in truth; yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it would not depart from its one pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty, that is, from it ſelf and its own.</p>
               <p>After this manner is knowledg without the love of that which is known, or hath been known; and thus it climbeth and creepeth to ſuch an height, that it ſuppoſeth
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:121281:58"/>it ſelf to know God and the true and ſimple truth, and ſo it loveth it ſelf in it ſelf. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God is known of nothing but of God; and becauſe this light ſuppoſeth that it knows God, it perſwads it ſelf alſo that it is God, and boaſteth it ſelf as God, and willing to be eſteemed God, thinking it ſelf worthy of all things, and to have right over all things, and that it hath over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come and conquered all things, &amp;c. Yea, it ſcorneth Chriſt himſelf, and the life of Chriſt, and all other things, for it would not be Chriſt but God eternal; the reaſon of this is, becauſe that Chriſt and his life is contrary and burthenſom to all nature, and therefore nature cannot bear it, but would be God for ever, and not man, yet would it willingly be Chriſt, as he is now after his reſurrection, for all this is eaſie, and pleaſant, and comfortable to nature, therefore nature eſteems it beſt, becauſe it ſeemeth beſt for her ſelf.</p>
               <p>Some thing is known, but yet not loved of this falſe light, and of this falſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful love, but knowledg and learning is more loved then the thing it ſelf which is known.</p>
               <p>There is alſo knowledg which is called
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:121281:58"/>Science, and yet is not Science, and this is when a man ſuppoſeth by hearing, reading, and ſome ſingular knowledg and learning, many things are known to him, the which is called Science, and ſaith, that it knoweth this or that: And if you aske him whence he knoweth it, he will make anſwer, that he hath read it in books, &amp;c. And this is termed knowledg and ſcience, &amp;c. but it is belief, and not ſcience or knowledg; and by this ſcience or knowledg many things are underſtood and known, which are not loved.</p>
               <p>There is alſo a love which is altogether falſe; as when any thing is loved for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; as when a man loveth juſtice, to the end he might obtain ſomething by it, &amp;c. Alſo when any creature loveth another for ſomething of his own, or if the creature do love God for ſome end; then all theſe things are falſe; and this love is moſt proper to nature as it is nature; neither can nature, as it is nature, know or perform any other love then this; for if any one were able to perceive this, nature, as it is nature, loveth nothing but it ſelf; by this means ſomething is acknowledged to be good and not loved. But the true love is taught and directed by
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:121281:59"/>the true light and knowledg, and the true, eternal and divine light teacheth love to love nothing elſe but the true, ſimple and perfect good, and that for no other cauſe but for good; not that it deſireth to have this, or that, or any thing from it by way of reward, but only for the love of good, and becauſe it is good, and ought deſervedly to be loved. That which is thus known of the true light, muſt alſo neceſſarily be loved of the true love: Now the perfect good, which is called good, cannot be known but of the true light, and therefore muſt needs be loved when it is known.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLI.</hi> Of the true Love of God.</head>
               <p>THis alſo is to be obſerved; in what man ſoever the true light, or the true love is, in him the true and perfect good is known, and love of it ſelf; and this is done, not that he loveth it as himſelf, or as from himſelf, but as it is the true and ſimple good: and ſurely that which is perfect, neither can nor will love any thing, ſo far forth as it is loved of it, but the only true good; and becauſe it ſelf is that ſame thing, it neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:121281:59"/>followeth, that it ſelf ſhould love it ſelf, yet not it ſelf, as it ſelf, nor of it ſelf, as of it ſelf; but ſo, and in ſuch manner, as one and the true good doth love one true per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect good, and as the one true and perfect good: And hereupon it is ſaid, and is true, that God doth not love himſelf, as himſelf; for if there were any thing better then God, God would love it, and not himſelf: For in this true light, and in this true love, there neither remaineth I, or mine, or to me, or thou, or thine, or any ſuch things; but the light knoweth and underſtandeth that one good, which is all good, and above all good; and all things are truly good in this one, and without this one there is no good. Therefore here, this, or that, I or thou, or the like, is not loved, but only that One, which is neither I, nor thou, this, nor that, and in it every good is loved, as the only good, as it is ſaid, all in one, as in one, and one in all, as in all; and one and all good is loved by one in one, or by the love of one, for the love that is born to one. Here it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that all Egoity, mine, ſelfneſs, and the like, ſhould wholy periſh and be forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and this belongeth properly to God, excepting what belongeth to the perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</p>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:121281:60"/>
               <p>Whatſoever therefore cometh to paſs in a man who is truly deified, either by doing or ſuffering, the ſame comes to paſs in this light or in this love, and from the ſame, and by the ſame, and again into the ſame; hence it followeth that man is contented with it, and giveth over his deſire to know more or leſs, or to have, live, dye, or not to be, &amp;c. all theſe things are effected and are one and the ſame; neither is any thing here blamed but only ſin; and what ſin is, is formerly ſaid: For it is ſin to will otherwiſe then the ſimple and perfect good, or the one and eternal will, and to will any thing without it, or againſt it, or otherwiſe then that only will would; whatſoever proceedeth thence, as to lye, injuſtice, fraud, and all vices. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, whatſoever is, and is called ſin, cometh hence, that man willeth otherwiſe then God, the true good: For if there were no will but this only one, there would be no ſin committed. Therefore we may well ſay, that all our own will is ſin, and that ſin is nothing elſe but that which proceeds from our will; and this is only that whereof a true deified man doth complain, and indeed he is ſo far grieved and moved with, as that, if ſuch a man were to endure
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:121281:60"/>a hundred infamous cruel deaths, he would not ſo much complain or grieve, as for ſin. And this muſt of neceſſity continue ſo until the death of the body; where ſuch a one is wanting, here ſurely is not a divine or dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied man. Therefore after that in this light and in this love all good is loved in one, and as one, and one in all, and in all things, as one, and as all, it followeth neceſſarily, that whatſoever hath truly a good name, ſhould alſo be loved, as vertue, order, integrity, juſtice, truth, &amp;c. Briefly, whatſoever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to God, as the true good, being proper to it, the ſame is beloved and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended of it: And whatſoever is contrary hereunto, or voyd of this, breedeth pain and torment, and is blamed, as ſin: And in what man ſoever this is beloved, in the true light and true love, he leadeth the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, beſt, and worthieſt life of any that ever was or ſhall be; and therefore this is to be affected and praiſed above all other lives: This was and is in Chriſt moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, otherwiſe he could not be Chriſt, and this love, of which all this excellent life and all good is loved, cauſeth all, whatſoever is meet, convenient, or ought to be ſuffered, done, or come to paſs, to be willingly and
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:121281:61"/>freely done and ſuffered, though it be or might be grievous to nature.</p>
               <p>Again, Chriſt ſaith, <hi>My yoke is eaſie, and my burthen light:</hi> this is wrought by that love which loveth this excellent life, and it is apparent in the Apoſtles and Martyrs, who ſuffered willingly and patiently what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they were to ſuffer: neither did they deſire of God that the torment and pain might be ſhortned and made eaſie or leſs, but only that they might abide firm and conſtant. And ſurely whatſoever is proper to the divine love in a truly deified man, the ſame is ſo ſimple, right, and plain, that it can never be plainly and truly expreſſed and written, neither can it be known, but only where it is: and where it is not, it cannot be loved, much leſs known.</p>
               <p>Again, natural life, where there is a crafty, nimble and uncertain nature, is ſo manifold and intricate, that it always ſeeks and finds many corners of falſhoods, deceits, and that only for it ſelf, ſo as that it cannot be expreſſed or written.</p>
               <p>Seeing then falſhood is deceived, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry deceit doth firſt deceive it ſelf, it follows, that the ſame thing muſt befall this falſe light and love; for he that deceiveth is falſe
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:121281:61"/>himſelf, as is elſe-where ſaid; And what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is proper to the Devil and belongs to him, is likewiſe in this life and light, and in the love thereof, in ſo much that there is no difference between them, and therefore that falſe light is the devil, and the devil is the ſelf-ſame light. This may hence appear, even as the Devil doth ſuppoſe himſelf to be God, and at leaſt would willingly be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted God, or eſteemed as God, and is in all this deceived, yea ſo far deceived that he thinketh he is not deceived: ſo it cometh to paſs likewiſe in the falſe light. &amp; in the love and life therof. And as the Devil would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly deceive all men, and draw them to him, and to his properties, making them like to himſelf, and uſing many arts and devices to that end, ſo the ſame comes to paſs like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in this light: And as no man can thruſt the devil out of his poſſeſſion, even ſo the like befalleth here. All this proceedeth hence, that the Devil and Nature both ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine and perſwade themſelves that they are not deceived, but rather that they are in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good eſtate, which truly is the worſt, and moſt hurtful error that can be. Therfore the Devil and Nature are one and the ſame; Overcome Nature, and you overcome the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:121281:62"/>Devil and vanquiſh him; and as long as Nature is unconquered, the Devil is alſo unconquered; Whether this be referred to a worldly, or ſpiritual life, yet all this light remaineth falſe and erroneous, being it ſelf deceived, and deceiving others alſo, if it can.</p>
               <p>By that which is formerly ſaid, it may e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently be underſtood, and known, that there is no difference, when and where there is any ſpeech made of <hi>Adam,</hi> diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, the old man, egoity, every mans own will, luſt, appetite, I, mine, nature, and falſe light, the devil, and ſin; all theſe are one and the ſame thing, all this is againſt God and without God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLII.</hi> That there is nothing contrary to God, but mans own will.</head>
               <p>BUt if now any one ask, whether there be any thing contrary to God and the true good? I anſwer, that there is nothing, either contrary to God, nor without God, but only to will otherwiſe then the eternal will willeth. If thou willeſt any thing other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then the eternal will willeth, that is contrary to the eternal will. Now the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:121281:62"/>will willeth, and requireth, that nothing ſhould be willed or loved, but only the true good; and if any thing be done other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, that is contrary to it. Hence it is, that this ſaying is true, <hi>That he who is not with God, is againſt God:</hi> but in very deed, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is againſt God, or the true good; which is thus to be underſtood, as if God had ſaid, he that willeth of himſelf without me, or willeth not as I do, or willeth other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then I do, he willeth againſt me; for my will is, that no man ſhould will other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then I do, or without me; and there ought to be no will without my will: As without me there is neither eſſence nor life, neither this nor that, ſo ought there alſo to be no will without me, or without my will: and truly, as all things, which are, are indeed one and the ſame in true eſſence, and every good is one good, neither can any thing be without that one; ſo alſo ought all wills to be one will in one perfect will, neither ought any will to be without this one; when therefore it is otherwiſe, it is juſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to God and his will, and therefore ſin. You ſee it hath been formerly ſaid, That e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very will, which is voyd of the will of God, that is, every proper will, and whatſoever
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:121281:63"/>proceedeth from the ſelf-will, is ſin; ſo long as man ſeeketh his own good, and that which is beſt for himſelf, as his own, to himſelf, and as of himſelf, he doth never ' find it; for as long as this is done, man ſeeks not not that which is beſt for himſelf, and therefore is far from finding of it: For ſo long as man is thus affected, he ſeeks him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and ſuppoſeth himſelf to be the beſt: and becauſe man is not the beſt ſo long as he ſeeks himſelf; but in what man ſoever good is ſought, loved, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected, as good, and for good, and that none otherwiſe but only for the love of good, not as from me, I, mine, to me, or for me, &amp;c. there it is found, for that it is rightly ſought; where it is otherwiſe, it is falſe: And truly, by this means the perfect good is ſought, and loved, and reſpected, and therefore found. It is a great folly in any man, to think that he knoweth or can do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing of himſelf, eſpecially when he thinketh that he knoweth, or can do any good, whereby he might attain or deſerve any great matter at Gods hands; for here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by God is diſhonored, if you rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it. Notwithſtanding that true good doth favor every ſimple and fooliſh man
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:121281:63"/>who knows no better things, and doth ſuffer the beſt things to befall him as much as may be; and ſurely God granteth him as much good as he is able to receive: but, as it is formerly ſaid, he neither findeth nor ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth it, ſo long as he is ſo affected; for he muſt neceſſarily forſake egoity wholy, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe he ſhall not find it, nor obtain it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLIII.</hi> That where the life of Chriſt is, there is Chriſt.</head>
               <p>HE that knoweth and underſtandeth the life of Chriſt, knoweth alſo and underſtandeth Chriſt: Again, he that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not the life of Chriſt, knoweth not Chriſt: He that beleeveth in Chriſt, belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth that his life is moſt excellent, and the beſt life; he that beleeveth not this, neither doth he beleeve in Chriſt. Look how much of the life of Chriſt is in any man, ſo much of Chriſt is in him alſo; and how little there is of the one, ſo little there is of the other. For where the life of Chriſt is, there is Chriſt; and where his life is not, neither is Chriſt there. Whereſoever therfore the life of Chriſt is, or may be, there that might be
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:121281:64"/>ſaid to be, which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>I live, yet not I, but Chriſt that liveth in me;</hi> and this is the beſt and moſt excellent life: for whereſoever this life is, there God himſelf is, and liveth, and likewiſe all good: Can there then be any better life then this? Obſerve this well; whenſoever you hear o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience ſpoken of, the new man, the true light, true love, or the life of Chriſt, all theſe are one and the ſame; and whereſoever one of theſe is abiding, they are all there like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; where one is wanting, none are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, for they are all true, and indeed one thing: But if there be any ſuch things, by the help whereof you may obtain that this might grow and live in man, you ought to cleave unto it, and to no other thing; and whatſoever doth hinder it, that you ought to leave and forſake: And if any man could obtain it in the holy Sacraments, he ſhould obtain Chriſt truly and well; and the more that you obtain of this, the more you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of Chriſt truly; and the leſs of this, the leſs alſo of Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="chapter">
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:121281:64"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLIV.</hi> ☞ To be content with God.</head>
               <p>IT is ſaid, That he who is contented with God, hath ſufficient, which is true; and he which is content with any thing elſe, which is this, or that, is not contented with God; but he that is content with God, is content with nothing elſe, but only with one, which is neither this, nor that, and yet it is all things; for God is one, and God is all things, and it is neceſſary that he ſhould be all things. Again, whatſoever is, and is not one, that is not God; and whatſoever is, and is not all, and above all, that is not God; for God is one, and all, and above all; whoſoever therefore is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with God, is content with one. And he to whom all things are not one, and one all things, and unto whom ſomething and nothing are not of like value, and are one and the ſame, he cannot be contented with God: But in whom this is, in him it is found, that he is contented, and no where elſe. The like is alſo to be here underſtood: He that will ſhew and approve himſelf holy, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable, and obedient to God, muſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily be conformable and obedient only in
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:121281:65"/>ſuffering, and neither reſiſt, help, nor defend himſelf: he that doth not ſo conform him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, &amp; become wholy obedient both to men, and all things, obeying in one, and as in one, he is not conformable, nor doth obey God. This we may ſee in Chriſt: To the end therefore that man may ſuffer God, and have a will ſo to do, it is neceſſary that he ſuffer all things in one, as in one; and that he do not in any ſort reſiſt any thing that is contrary to him; This Chriſt alſo perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: And he that reſiſteth thoſe things which are croſs to him. &amp; guardeth himſelf againſt them, neither will nor can ſuffer God: This is thus to be underſtood; Reſiſtance ought not to be made againſt any thing, or crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, by force or war, by will or work; yet it is lawful, without committing ſin, to foreſee, avoyd, and fly thoſe things which are hurtful to us. Therefore he that goeth about or willeth love to God, loveth all things, in one, as in one; and one in all things, as all things in one: Alſo he that loveth any thing, this, or that, otherwiſe then in one, and for one, he loveth not God, becauſe he loveth ſomething which is not God, and therefore he loveth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more then God: He then that loveth
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:121281:65"/>any thing more then God, or loveth any thing beſides God, loveth not God; for God will and ought to be only loved, and nothing ought truly to be loved but God: And in what man ſoever the true light and true love is, there is nothing loved of him ſaving God, for God is there loved, as God, and for God, and all that is good, as one, and one, as all, for all things are truly one, and one is all in God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLV.</hi> Whether ſin is to be loved.</head>
               <p>HEre ariſeth a queſtion; ſince that all things are to be loved, whether ſin ought to be loved? I anſwer, No; for when all is mentioned, that only is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood which is good, and every thing is good in that it is: The Devil is good in that he is; and in this manner nothing is evil or not good: But it is ſin, to will, deſire, or love, otherwiſe then God doth; and to will this, is not to be, and therefore it is not good. Briefly, there is nothing good, but ſo far forth as it is in God; now all things are that which they are, in God,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:121281:66"/>and that a great deal more then in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; therefore all things are good ſo far forth as they are: and if there were any thing, whoſe eſſence were not in God, that that thing were not good; but to will, or deſire any thing, which is againſt God, is not in God; for God cannot deſire or will any thing againſt God, nor otherwiſe then God doth; therefore it is evil and not good, or rather it is nothing at all: God alſo loveth works, but not all manner of works: What work doth he love? Surely ſuch as proceed from the teaching and diſcipline of the true light, and from true love; whatſoever pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from theſe, and is done therein, in ſpirit and truth, the ſame belongeth to God, as is pleaſing to him; but that which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from the falſe light, and falſe love, all that is evil, and eſpecially that which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth, cometh to paſs, is done, or left un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, or is ſuffered to be done by or from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny otherwil or deſire, or any other love, then from the will, or love of God: All this, I ſay, is, and cometh to paſs, without God, and againſt God, and is alſo againſt the work of God, and is ſin.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="chapter">
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:121281:66"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLVI.</hi> That Faith bringeth forth Knowledg.</head>
               <p>CHriſt ſaid, He who doth not, or can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, or will not beleeve, is loſt and damned; this is true: For what man ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver comes into this life, neither hath know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, not can attain to it, except he firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve; and he that will needs know, before he beleeve, never comes to true knowledg: Theſe things are not to be underſtood of the chief points of Chriſtian Faith; for all and every Chriſtian of the common people doth beleeve them, the wicked as well as the innocent, the evil as well as the good: Theſe are to be beleeved, elſe no man can come to the knowledg of the other: Theſe things are to be underſtood of the occaſions belonging to truth, which may both be known and found out; theſe muſt be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved before they be known or found out, elſe it is impoſſible to come to true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg: And of this Faith Jeſus Chriſt ſpeaketh.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="chapter">
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:121281:67"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLVII.</hi> Of mans own proper will.</head>
               <p>IT is ſaid, That in Hell nothing aboundeth ſo much as ſelf-will, and this is true, for there is none other but ſelf-will; and if it were not ſo, there would be neither Hell nor Devil. Whereas it is ſaid, That the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil fell down from Heaven, and averted himſelf from God, &amp;c. it it nothing elſe but that he would have his own will, and not be of the ſame will with the eternal will. The like befell <hi>Adam</hi> alſo in Paradiſe: And where mention is made of ſelf-will, then that is underſtood to be it, which willeth otherwiſe then the ſimple and eternal will would, or willeth. But what is Paradiſe? It is whatſoever is: for whatſoever is, is good, and pleaſant, and alſo pleaſing to God; and therefore both is, and is rightly called Paradiſe. Paradiſe is alſo ſaid to be the threſhold or ſuburbs of the Kingdom of Heaven; ſo alſo, whatſoever is, may be well termed the ſuburbs of the eternal, or of the eternity; chiefly, that which may be perceived or known, in this life, from temporary things, in the creatures, and out of the creatures of God, and eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:121281:67"/>For the creatures are a demonſtration and way which leadeth to God and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, therefore they are called a threſhold and ſuburbs of eternity; and he may well be ſaid to be the Paradiſe. In this Paradiſe all things were granted; which were in it, except one tree and the fruit thereof; which is thus to be underſtoud: There is nothing forbidden of all things which are there, nor contrary to God, ſaving one thing, which is our own proper will, or that man ſhould will otherwiſe then the eternal will willeth. This is to be weighed: God ſaith unto <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, id eſt,</hi> to every particular man, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever thou doſt, or doſt not, that is lawful, and not forbidden, ſo as it be done, not out of thy will, nor according to the ſame, but out of mine, and after mine, for whatſoever is done out of thy will, that is wholy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary unto the eternal will, not becauſe all works ſo done are contrary unto the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal will, but ſaving only when they are done with another will, or otherwiſe then out of the eternal will.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="chapter">
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:121281:68"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLVIII.</hi> Why God did create mans own will, ſeeing it is contrary to the eternal will.</head>
               <p>HEre ſome will ask; ſeeing that this Tree (<hi>id eſt,</hi> our own proper will) is ſo contrary to God, and the eternal will, why did God create and make it, and alſo place it in Paradiſe? Unto which I thus an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; If any man, or creature, deſire to ſearch into, and know the hidden Counſel and Will of God, as longing to underſtand why God did any thing, or left it undone, or ſuch like, this man deſireth the ſame that <hi>Adam</hi> and the Devil did; and whilſt this deſire laſteth, the matter is never known, neither is this man any other, but ſuch a one as <hi>Adam</hi> and the Devil; for this deſire ſeldom proceeds from any other motion then that thou takeſt pleaſure and glorieſt therein, which is meer pride. A truly humbled and illuminated man doth not deſire of God to have his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets revealed to him, as if he ſhould ask, why God did do, or delay to do this or that? &amp;c. But on the contrary part, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth only that himſelf might be annihilated in himſelf, and that his own will might pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, and the eternal will live and prevail in
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:121281:68"/>him, remained unhindered of any other wils, and that he himſelf, and all that is in him, might ſatisfie the eternal will; yet ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe might be ſaid in anſwer to this queſtion, after this wiſe: There is nothing ſo excellent and pleaſing in all creatures, as knowledg, or reaſon, and will: which two are ſo joyned together, that where the one is, there is the other alſo; and if theſe two were not, then would there be no reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble creature at all, but only bruit beaſt, and bruitiſhneſs, which would be a great fault: Neither would God (as it is ſaid formerly ſaid) obtain his own nature, or the nature of thoſe who are his, by acting, which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notwithſtanding is fit to be done, and apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth to perfection. Now this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, and created reaſon, was given with the will, to the end it might both inſtruct the will, and it ſelf, that neither the knowledg nor the will was of it ſelf, and that neither of them had part of themſelves, nor ought to ſerve themſelves, nor their own will, and that neither of them ought to be profitable to it ſelf, or to the uſe of it ſelf, but to be of his of whom they had their Being, and to obey and flow back again into him, and in themſelves, that ſame is to be turned into nothing in their own ſelfneſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="chapter">
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:121281:69"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLIX.</hi> Why God created the will.</head>
               <p>HEre again is ſomething eſpecially to be obſerved concerning the will, the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal will, which is in God originally and eſſentially, without any work or action, the ſame will is likewiſe man, and all other li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving things, both doing and willing: for the nature and property of the will is to will; for what other things ſhould it do? for it ſhould not be at all if it had no action, and this cannot be effected without living crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; Therefore it is neceſſary that there ſhould be creatures, and God wil have ſuch, to the end that this will might have and do its own work in them, which otherwiſe is in God without work, and yet cannot but be: Therefore there is a will in living crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which is called a created will, no leſs belonging to God, then the eternal will is not appertaining to the creature: And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God cannot will with action and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, without living creatures, therefore he will do it in and with the living creatures: Wherefore living things ought not to will any thing by this very will, but God ought and will, by action, will together, with the
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:121281:69"/>will which is in man, and yet is the will of God, which if it were any where, or that this were in man, abſolutely or wholly, then men ſhould will nothing but only God, and there I ſay will ſhould not be ſelf-will, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould that man will otherwiſe then God willeth, for God ſhould there exerciſe his will and not man, and there the will of man ſhould be the ſame with the eternal will, as having flowed into the ſame: And in man there would be and remain love and ſorrow, pleaſure and pain, with ſuch like: For where the will doth will willingly, there is love or ſorrow: whereſoever thoſe things are put in execution, which the will willeth, there is love; but if other things be done then the will willeth, there is ſorrow, and this ſorrow is not mans, but Gods; for whoſe the will is, his alſo is the love and ſorrow, and this love and ſorrow is not mans but Gods, but the wil is not the wil of man, but of God; therefore the love and ſorrow is his alſo; neither is there any thing blamed, ſaving that which is contrary to God: neither is there any joy or pleaſure conceived, but what proceedeth from God, and from that which is Gods, and belongeth to God. Therefore, as it is with the will, ſo it is with
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:121281:70"/>knowledg, reaſon, power, love, and all things which are in man, <hi>id eſt,</hi> that they all belong to God, and not to man: And if it ſhould come to paſs, at any time, that the will were wholly forſaken, then all other things would likewiſe be abandoned, and by this means God ſhould obtain all things appertaining unto him, and will ſhould be no more ſelf-will: Thus did God create will, but not that it ſhould be our own.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. L.</hi> How the Devil and <hi>Adam</hi> challenge will to themſelves.</head>
               <p>NOw cometh the Devil and <hi>Adam,</hi> (<hi>id est,</hi> falſe nature) and challengeth unto himſelf this will, making it his own, and enjoying it to the uſe of himſelf, and thoſe which are his; and this is the great loſs and injury: This, I ſay, is that bit wherewith <hi>Adam</hi> did bite the apple, which is forbidden, and contrary to God. And as long, and where this ſelf-will is, there never is any true quietneſs, which may eaſily be diſcerned both in man, and alſo in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil: Neither is there verily any true happy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs there, either in this life or everlaſtingly.
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:121281:70"/>Where this ſelf-will is, there is a propriety, by which man doth challenge will unto himſelf, and maketh it his own; which if it be not forſaken in this life, but carryed forth of this life, it is to be feared that it can never be abandoned, neither can that man ever receive true contentment, nor enjoy peace, reſt, or happyneſs: The which may be ſeen in the Devil. If creatures were not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with reaſon and will, ſurely God would remain unknown and unbelieved, neither praiſed nor honoured, and all living creatures would be of no aceount, and unfit to ſerve God; and this anſwer is made to this queſtion: If there be any one, who from this long and tedious ſpeech, (which notwithſtanding is ſhort and profitable to Godwards) can and will correct himſelf, that will be very acceptable to God. That which is free, is proper to no man, and he that doth appropriate it, doth ill. Now, of all freedoms, nothing is ſo free as the wil, and whoſoever maketh it his own, and doth not leave it to its own noble liberty, free nobleneſs &amp; free nature, he doth ill; this doth the Devil and <hi>Adam,</hi> and all their Imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors; but he that doth leave will to its own excellent liberty, doth as he ought: This
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:121281:71"/>doth Chriſt, and all that imitate him. He that depriveth will of that his excellent li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and maketh it his own, this mans re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward is, that he becometh ſubject to cares, ſorrows, poverties, troubles, unquietneſs and misfortunes, and that he remain in them ſo long as that laſteth, both in this life and for ever. But he that leaveth will to its own free nature, he enjoyeth plenty, peace, quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, reſt, felicity, both in this life and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly. Wherfore, where, and in what man will is not appropriated, but remaineth in its own excellent freedom, there abideth, and is a truly free and abſolute man, or creature, of whom Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Truth ſhall make you free,</hi> and preſently after, <hi>Whom the Son doth make free, he is free indeed.</hi> John 8.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. LI.</hi> That in what man the truth is, in that man free-will is.</head>
               <p>THis alſo is diligently to be obſerved; That in what man ſoever the truth uſeth its free liberty, it hath a work proper to it ſelf, which is to will, and that which it willeth, it willeth without hinderance, and it willeth that which in every thing is the
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:121281:71"/>beſt and moſt excellent; and whatſoever is not excellent, nor good, is contrary unto it, breedeth grief and complaint; and the freer the will is, and at liberty, the more ſorrow, pain, and cauſe of moan is brought upon it, by wickedneſs, diſhoneſty, malice, vice, and whatſoever is or can be termed ſin: This may be diſcerned in Chriſt, who was endued with a moſt free, abſolute, and leaſt-appropriated will, that ever was, or ſhall be in any man; yea, the huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Chriſt was a creature, moſt free, and at greateſt liberty of any man that ever was, and yet it ſuffered ſo much cauſe of complaint, miſery, and pain for ſin, (that is, for all things contrary to God) as never any creature was able to ſuffer more.</p>
               <p>But where man doth challenge liberty in ſuch ſort to himſelf, as that he will endure no cauſe of complaint, or miſery, for ſin, and ſuch thing as are contrary to God, but will neglect and free himſelf from all care, and would be in this life in the ſame condition wherein Chriſt was after his Reſurrection, &amp;c. There is no true liberty ariſing from the divine light, but a natural, unjuſt, falſe, erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous &amp; deviliſh liberty out of a natural life,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:121281:72"/>and erroneous light: If there were no ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will, there would be no propriety at all; in the Kingdom of Heaven, nothing is proper, and therefore there is full abundance, true peace, and all happpneſs; and if any one were there, who would challenge any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety to himſelf, he ſhould neceſſarily go to Hell, and become a Devil.</p>
               <p>But in Hell every one deſireth to have his own ſelf-will, and therefore there is all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happineſs and miſery; the like alſo happeneth in this life. But if there were any one in Hell, who could free himſelf from ſelf-will, and propriety, he ſhould come from Hell to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
               <p>Now man in this world is placed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Heaven and Hell, and may turn him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to either of them; for the more propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety he hath, the more he is ſubject to Hell and unhappineſs; and the leſs wil he hath, the leſs hel he hath, &amp; the neerer he is to the king dom of heaven. And if man in this preſent world could be utterly void of ſelf-will and propriety, and be free and abſolute, by means of the true and divine light, and ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main truly in that eſtate, this man ſhould be ſure to inherit the Kingdom of Heaven: He that hath, would have, or deſireth to have
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:121281:72"/>any thing proper to himſelf becometh pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and, as it were, his own ſlave and bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; but he that hath nothing, nor will have any thing, nor deſireth to have any thing proper to himſelf, he is free and at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and none hath propriety in him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. LII.</hi> Of Chriſt his Croſs.</head>
               <p>CHriſt did teach all theſe things, which are here written, in his long life, which was almoſt three and thirty years and a half; and this he did in few words, when he ſaid, <hi>Follow me.</hi> Now, that man may follow him, it is neceſſary that he forſake all things: for Chriſt forſook all things, ſo far forth as they never were ſo left of any other, nor could be: Further, he that would follow him, muſt alſo take up his Croſs, which Croſs is nothing elſe but the Life of Chriſt; for this Croſs is bitter to all nature: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſaith, <hi>Whoſoever doth not forſake all, and take up his Croſs, he is not worthy of me, and cannot be my Diſciple, neither doth he follow me.</hi> But the free, falſe nature ſuppoſeth that it hath forſaken all things, yet will not endure the Croſs, and ſaith, that
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:121281:73"/>it hath endured enough of it, and that now it ſtandeth in no need of it, but therein it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for if it had once truly taſted the Croſs, it could never forſake it: He that beleeveth in Chriſt, muſt beleeve all things that are written: Chriſt ſaith, <hi>No man co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to the Father, but by me:</hi> Now ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, how we muſt come to the Father by Chriſt; man ought to examine himſelf, and all things that are his, both inwardly and outwardly, and ſo behave and help himſelf, ſo far as he can, that in him there never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main or be inwardly any evil or deſire, love or eſtimation, thought or pleaſure, other then becometh God, and is lawful, even as if God himſelf were man himſelf; but when it is found that there is any thing which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh not God, neither is lawful, that ought to be pluckt up by the roots, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted as ſoon and as well as may be: the like ought alſo to be done outwardly, in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or not doing, in ſpeaking or being ſilent, waking or ſleeping. Laſtly, in all Ceremony or matters, which man uſeth, either with themſelves or with others, or towards himſelf, or towards others; in all theſe let care be had that nothing elſe happen, nor that man convert himſelf to any other thing,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:121281:73"/>or ſuffer any other thing to abide, or be in him, either outwardly or inwardly; and that nothing elſe be done by him, but that which is worthy of God, and may juſtly and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully be done, even as if God himſelf were man himſelf: In ſuch a man, whatſoever is, or might be, or is, or may be done inwardly or outwardly, that is or ſhould be Gods: And man is or muſt be an Imitator of the Life of Chriſt, which life we may underſtand and publiſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. LIII.</hi> Of the Imitation of Christ.</head>
               <p>IF then any man could attain to this life, he ſhould go and come through Chriſt to the Father, for therein he ſhould be an Imitator of Chriſt; and therefore ſhould come with Chriſt to the Father, and by Chriſt, and ſhould be the true ſervant of Chriſt; for he that followeth him, (as himſelf ſaith) <hi>He that will ſerve me, let him follow me:</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, He that doth not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me, doth not ſerve me: He, I ſay, who doth thus follow Chriſt, and ſerve him, he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treth into the ſame place where Chriſt is, <hi>id eſt,</hi> to the Father. This our Lord Chriſt doth
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:121281:74"/>affirm, when he ſaith, <hi>Father, I will that where I am, there my ſervants be alſo:</hi> He that goeth this way, enters by the door into the ſheepfold, that is, into eternal life, and the Porter openeth the door unto him; but he that goeth, or endeavoureth another way, or ſuppoſeth that he can come to the Father, or eternal happineſs, otherwiſe then by Chriſt, he is in an error, for he goeth not the right way, neither entereth at the door, and therefore it is not opened unto him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is a thief and a robber, as Chriſt himſelf faith: Mark then, whether by inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate liberty, contentiouſneſs, negligence, vertue or-vice, order or confuſion, &amp;c. as you may eaſily perceive; Whether (I ſay) one may thus enter by a right way, or at a right door, or not? This negligence was neither in Chriſt, nor any of his followers. Chriſt alſo ſaith, <hi>No man comes to me, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept my Father draw him;</hi> which you muſt thus underſtand: I underſtand the Father to be the perfect and ſimple good, which is all, and above all, and without which there never was, nor ſhall be any good work wrought; and becauſe he is all in all, it is neceſſary that he ſhould be alone, &amp; above all things, which a creature, as a creature, is able
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:121281:74"/>to underſtand or comprehend. For what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever a creature can comprehend or under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, as it is a creature, that is, according to the condition of his creation, the ſame is ſomething, either this or that, and further it is a creature: But if the ſimple and perfect were ſomething, this or that, which the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture might comprehend, then that would not be all, nor alone, neither yet perfect, and in that reſpect it ſhould not be ſo much as named: For we muſt think that it is none of theſe things which the creature, by his own nature, is able to underſtand, compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, or name. When this perfect and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominable good doth flow into a begetting perſon, in which he may beget his only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Son and himſelf, it is is named Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. LIV.</hi> How the Father draweth to the Son, and the Son reciprocally to the Father.</head>
               <p>COnſider and obſerve, how the Father draweth men to Chriſt, which is after this manner; when any thing is made known, and laid open, by this perfect God, to the ſoul, or unto man, there is begotten in
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:121281:75"/>man, as it were, in one moment, and one vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent rapture, a certain deſire of approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the perfect good, and joyning it ſelf with it: The greater that this deſire is, the more things are revealed unto it, and the more it deſireth, and is drawn nearer to it. Thus man is drawn and ſtirred up to joyn with the eternal good, and this is the attraction of the Father; and after man is taught, that is, of the Son which draweth him, <hi>viz,</hi> that he cannot come to this Communion by any other means then by the Life of Chriſt; and thus it comes to paſs, that he purchaſeth to himſelf the life whereof we have formerly ſpoken.</p>
               <p>Now obſerve theſe two ſayings, which Chriſt ſpeaketh; the one is this, <hi>No man co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to the Father, but by me, id eſt,</hi> by my life, as hath been formerly ſaid. The other is, <hi>No man cometh unto me,</hi> that is, to be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of my life, and to follow me; <hi>except he be drawn and taught of my Father,</hi> that is, by the ſimple and eternal good, of which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>When that which is perfect is come, then that which is in part ſhall be aboliſhed:</hi> The meaning whereof is this; In what man ſoever the perfect good is known, found and felt, ſo far forth as
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:121281:75"/>may be in this life, to that man all things that are created ſeem to be nothing, in regard of this perfect good, as indeed they are nothing at all: For where that which is perfect is not, there is no true good, nor true being; he therefore that hath, knoweth and loveth this perfect good, he hath, knoweth and loveth all things, and all good: What ſhould he then do with more, or other things? or what ſhould he do with the parts? ſeeing that all the parts are joyned and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in this perfect good in one eſſence.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. LV.</hi> How God becometh all things in man.</head>
               <p>ALL that is here ſaid belongeth to the outward life, and is a certain way and paſſage unto the true inward life, and the inward life beginneth according to this: When man would taſte that which is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, as far as may be, all things which are created, and even man himſelf is brought to nought in this mans opinion: But if it be truly underſtood, that only perfection is all things, and above all things, then it doth neceſſarily follow hence, that we do acknowledg every good thing to
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:121281:76"/>belong unto this perfect good, and not to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny creature, as to eſſence, life, knowledg, ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, power, &amp;c. then it followeth, that man ſhould arrogate nothing to himſelf, not life, eſſence, power, knowledg, doing or not doing; Finally nothing that can be called good: So man becometh poor, and is in himſelf brought to nothing, alſo, in him, and with him, every thing that is ſomething, <hi>id eſt,</hi> all things created, and then at laſt exiſteth the true and inward life, and further, God himſelf; ſo that there is nothing more there, which is not God, or belonging to God: Neither is there any thing which doth chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge or arrogate any thing to it ſelf; ſo that it cometh to paſs that it is God only who liveth, underſtandeth, is able, loveth, willeth, doeth, or leaveth undone: That is, the eternal and perfect good ought thus to be, and where it is otherwiſe, there the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter might be both better and ſtreighter: For a good work and beginning, if care be had that it be the beſt, becometh moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable, and let the beſt be choſen and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hered unto, alſo let man joyn himſelf to it thing in the creatures? But what is the beſt thing in the creatures? Surely where the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal good, and that which is proper unto
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:121281:76"/>it, doth enlighten and work, and where they are moſt known and loved. And what is that which belongeth to God, and is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per only to him? I ſay, all that is it, which may be truly and rightly called and named good, when man in the creatures adhereth and cleaveth ſo to that which is known to be the beſt, as that he remaineth ſtedfaſt, and flyeth not back; then it comes to paſs that he attaineth to ſomething which is better then it, ſo far forth, until man perceive and underſtand, that that only eternal and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect good is unmeaſurable, infinite, and to be eſteemed above all created goodneſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. LVI.</hi> That God alone is to be loved and honored.</head>
               <p>THerefore if that which is beſt ought moſt of all to be loved, and if man do follow it, then the only eternal good ought, without doubt, alone, to be loved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things, and man ought to ſtick thereunto only, and to joyn himſelf unto it, ſo far as is in his power: And if every good thing ought to be acknowledged, as received from the eternal only good (as worthily and truly it ought) then alſo the
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:121281:77"/>beginning, going forward, and concluſion, ought rightly and truly to be acknowledged and eſteemed from it, and the ſame ought to be imputed and adjudged to it, ſo as nothing is left as appertaining to man, or the creatures; and thus it ought of right to be. And whatſoever is ſaid, or alledged, as againſt this, yet this is the way which leadeth into the true interiour life: But what will at laſt become of this, or be manifeſted there, or what manner of life this is like to prove<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> no man uttereth or expreſſeth, neither was it ever declared, or did any heart either know or conceive truly the quality of ſuch a life. It is briefly contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this long written diſcourſe, by what means it may rightly and truly come to paſs that man become free and voyd of arroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting any thing to himſelf, or from willing, wiſhing, loving, or affecting any thing, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God and Divinity, that is the eternal, perfect, and only good; and if any man arrogate to himſelf, will, eſteem, or deſire any thing, other, or more then the eternal good, it is too much and vicious. Briefly, if a man can obtain ſo far forth as to be the ſame to God which the hand of man is to man, let him reſt therewith contented: And
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:121281:77"/>this ought truly to be done for all breathing creatures, eſpecially thoſe who are endued with Reaſon; and chiefly man doth truly and deſervedly ow this duty to God: This you may gather out of what hath been formerly written. This alſo is to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to memory, after man hath proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo far as that he ſhould verily perſwade himſelf to have attained hereunto, it is time then that he ſhould have regard, leſt the Devil ſowing aſhes there, he ſeek and repoſe his whole nature, tranquillity, reſt, peace and pleaſure in it, and ſo ſlide into fooliſh, and inordinate liberty, and negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, which truly is wholy repugnant and remote from the divine life; this befalleth that man, who neither hath, nor will enter in at the right gate, nor by the right way, that is, by Chriſt, as is aforeſaid; but will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and thinketh that he may attain to this perfect truth, otherwiſe &amp; by other means; or elſe conceiveth that he hath attained ſo far already, before he come to it in truth, <hi>id eſt,</hi> manifeſt by the witneſs of Chriſt; who ſaith, <hi>He that will enter by any other means then by me, he never entreth rightly, nor hath attained the chief truth, but is a chief and a robber,</hi> That we may depart from our
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:121281:78"/>and being dead to our own wills, live only to God, and the performance of his will; God grant, through him, who ſubjected his will to the will of his heavenly Father; who alſo liveth and raigneth with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Unity of the Holy Ghoſt, and the perfect Trinity everlaſtingly. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="sayings">
               <head>Certain grave ſayings, by which the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Schollar of Chriſt may ſearch into himſelf, and know what is to be ſought and ſtrived for concerning the true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward uniting of himſelf to the one ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream good.</head>
               <p>GOd is one, and unity exiſteth, and floweth from him alone, and yet not out of him, otherwiſe it ſhould decreaſe and become leſs.</p>
               <p>Where two are, which ought to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, and agree together, it is poſſible that betwixt thoſe diſcord ſhould ariſe.</p>
               <p>Theſe two cannot diſagree, ſaving only in will, which would be the greateſt cauſe of all diſcord in God himſelf, if two things could be in him.</p>
               <p>For there is nothing which may breed
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:121281:78"/>diſagreement amongſt all things, which may diſagree, but diſſimilitude of wills.</p>
               <p>This one God willeth that which is one, and is contrary to all things, which are two; Therefore whatſoever he himſelf hath crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted he created upon this one, otherwiſe it ſhould have wanted order.</p>
               <p>Further, his Creation, or the things crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, could have had no conſtancy, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his contrary will, even as now it comes to paſs, and therefore it muſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily have periſhed.</p>
               <p>This Unity could not have been meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, conſidered, handled or known, but only of one, and through one, and that ſometimes in its contrary.</p>
               <p>Contrariety exiſteth of it ſelf without the fault of the Adverſary.</p>
               <p>Hence it may eaſily be diſcerned, that this one, and this beſt, was to have ſome object, from whence it, as far as might be, ſhould be known.</p>
               <p>That Object was and is the eſſence and being of all living things: Chiefly, and beſt, in the reaſonable, and by the reaſonable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which was <hi>Adam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here the omnipotency, mercy and infinite goodneſs doth ſhew it ſelf, whoſe name is</p>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:121281:79"/>
               <p>To the increaſing of further knowledg, hee created every thing free which he did craate: for whatſoever was, is, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m ineth free, could not man naturally make or create any thing that was proper.</p>
               <p>Now alſo that free thing could not more conveniently work in any thing, or make it ſelf apparent, then in its own object.</p>
               <p>He that concludeth and appropriateth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing that is free, and ought to be free, doth the contrary to him which made and created it free, this is ſin.</p>
               <p>Sin is plainly to be diſcerned, if you will throughly hate it.</p>
               <p>Hatred conſiſteth in that which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to it; which is truly named the ſeed of God, or the Image of God, and deſireth liberty without intermiſſion. This remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and is, and muſt neceſſarily ſo do, as long as God can be, and remaineth in that which it ſelf is, for it proceedeth from one, and never ſuffereth it ſelf to be drawn thence; that it might be both ſoon, and rightly made good again, that one, which is perfect, interpoſeth it ſelf, for the reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of all that to the full which was ſevered from it ſelf.</p>
               <p>This could, not be done but in ſome one
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:121281:79"/>thing, which ſhould pretend it ſelf diſ-joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, yet without all detriment to the unity.</p>
               <p>This was meet and convenient, yea, neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, to the end it might openly declare it ſelf ſo far forth as it is one, and that only one, whereby liberty might return to its own eſtate, which notwithſtanding it had never loſt.</p>
               <p>Hereupon it is that Jeſus of <hi>Nazareth</hi> taught, exerciſed and uſed the moſt abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute free will that might be.</p>
               <p>This was not his own (as himſelf witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth) but belonged only to him, of whom he had received it, that by him it might be made manifeſt: Yet could he not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of it, both in regard of his right, as alſo of his perfection, which he was neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily to have, in regard of the liberty, that he might declare the ſame in excellency, as it was meet. The entire and abſolute uniting of will was moſt perfect in him, which did not arrogate that to himſelf of which it ſelf was one, otherwiſe it had faln from that one.</p>
               <p>Now there remaineth yet; as hath been ſhewed, that free thing which is not to be forſaken or loſt, elſe it would damnifie the Divinity, from which it is, and to which is
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:121281:80"/>properly belongeth, for it would have loſt ſomething which would have gone to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and ſomething would have been, whereupon it might have followed, that the whole ſhould have periſhed after the ſame manner.</p>
               <p>That this therefore might be done, it is neceſſary that it ſhould be made according to the pattern, and that wholly anſwerable to the will and pleaſure of one which never diſagreed from it ſelf, which pattern muſt neceſſarily be the perfecteſt, in regard of its office.</p>
               <p>This is, and is called to return from all diſagreeing into that only one which we ought to endeavour all our life long: He that is willing, is able, and he that doth not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve it, let him make tryal.</p>
               <p>This may and ought to be done only by the loſs of that which is contrary to one, otherwiſe it is impoſſible; this is obedience in obedience; an entire yeeling up a certain perfect Sacrifice, which is volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily.</p>
               <p>To be ſhort, it is Chriſt, the true Son of God, the firſt begotten of brethren; to whom whatſoever the Father can do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly belongeth, who is the true Reconciler,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:121281:80"/>by whom only you may and ought neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily to come to the only one, that is, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; the which Father hath ordained him to this thing.</p>
               <p>If any one cannot attain to the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of this diſcourſe, he wanteth the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of the Spirit, the diſcipline whereof he excludeth and refuſeth. If any man un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it, let him judg, for the Spirit of God judgeth all things. If any man be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived hereof, and wants it, it is his own fault, becauſe he is not careful of his fall that it might be amended, which not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to be corrected. If any man ſay, that theſe things are over ſharp, let him know that the greateſt folly of the Holy Ghoſt (as I may ſo ſpeak) is more acute then the greateſt wiſdom in all the world.</p>
               <p>It is no wonder if theſe things ſeem ſharp to fleſh and blood, for they are Divine, of which the fleſh cannot judg, and therefore it eſteems them ſharp; even as if an Owl ſhould deny that ſhe could behold the brightneſs of the day, becauſe ſhe only u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the hight of the night, the moſt lightſom part whereof is darker then the moſt dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom part of the day.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="144" facs="tcp:121281:81"/>
            <head>The Authors Inſtitution contained in three points, wherein we learn how to forſake our ſelves, and to put on God by a most perfect way.</head>
            <p>THE firſt is, That every man aſpire to attain unto a more excellent degree of ſanctity, and ſingular embracing of God by love; alſo, that he love God with all the powers of his ſoul, and his neighbor as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; and that he deſire to feel God truly working in himſelf in this world: Such a one ought both to extinguiſh, and alſo to have extinguiſhed in him all delights and pleaſures, bred by ſuch mortal creatures as are without God, of what ſort ſoever they are.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is, That every one, both in this world, and in the world to come, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to attain to the perfect knowledg of truth, and that he prepare and contain him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf inwardly from being delighted in any ſort ſpiritually, with any thing, which he may challenge, claim or poſſeſs as his own, or as proper to himſelf.</p>
            <p>The third thing is, That after a man is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly and wholly, both inwardly and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, freed from adhering to any thing,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:121281:81"/>and hath learned to rely upon his own no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but then inſtantly he hath a ready and free paſſage to the pure and ſimple good, that Almighty and moſt excellent God. But this converſation is wrought by a certain eſſential way or means: For here the Spirit is turned to God, not in part, but wholly and entirely, whence this is ſaid, not only to be, but is a true, eſſential, entire and individed, and perfect converſion, for it is not withdrawn any whither from it ſelf, and therefore may be ſaid to be eſſential, and God himſelf doth ever anſwer it eſſentially.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Perfection in the firſt, ſecond, third and fourth degree.</head>
               <p>HE is truly and properly perfect in the firſt degree, who turneth his whole mind orderly and diſcreetly away from all viſible and tranſitory things.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond degree, who hath obtained a peaceable and quiet conſcience.</p>
               <p>In the third degree, who takes all things in good part from Gods hand, and reſigneth himſelf wholly to him.</p>
               <p>In the fourth degree, he who forgetting himſelf, and all creatures, doth loſe himſelf in God.</p>
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:121281:82"/>
               <p>HE that of vertue makes the trueſt gain,</p>
               <p>Seeks not reward, but labor for his pain.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>In war, that I am undertaking</l>
                  <l>Againſt my ſelf, my force doth ſpend me:</l>
                  <l>Sith with my ſelf war I am making,</l>
                  <l>O from my ſelf then God defend me.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Communication of Doctor <hi>Thaulerus</hi> with a poor beggar, wherein is compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended the example of a perfect man, and how we ſhould reſign our ſelves, in all things, unto the good pleaſure of God.</head>
               <p>THere was, on a time, a great Divine, who prayed unto God the ſpace of eight years, that it might be his good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to direct him to a man that might in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct and teach him the true way of vertue; And it happened, being in this deſire, that he heard a voyce from heaven, which ſaid unto him, Go unto ſuch a Church-porch, and there thou ſhalt find a man that will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:121281:82"/>thee in the ſpiritual life: He walking then towards the ſaid Church, found a poor beggar, who had his feet filthy and foul, and all naked, whoſe clothes were not worth a half-penny, and he ſaluted him in this ſort: God give you good morrow, my friend. The poor man anſwered him; Sir, I do not remember that ever I had an evil morrow. The Doctor ſaid unto him, God give you a good and happy life: Wherefore ſay you that, quoth the Beggar unto him, for I was never unhappy? Which the Doctor not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, ſaid unto him again God bleſs you, my friend: I pray you ſpeak a little more clearly, for I know not what you mean.</p>
               <p>Then the poor Beggar anſwered him; Good maſter Doctor, I ſhall do it willingly: You know you bade me good morrow; whereunto I replyed, that I had never any evil morrow: for when I have hunger I praiſe God: If it freeze, hail, ſnow, rain, be it fair or foul, I give praiſe to God; though I be poor, miſerable, and deſpiſed of each one, I give thanks unto God: and therefore I never had any evil morrow. You did wiſh unto me alſo a good and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py life; whereunto I made you anſwer,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:121281:83"/>that I was never unfortunate; becauſe I have learned always to reſign my ſelf unto the will of God, being certain that all his works cannot be but very good; by reaſon whereof, all that happeneth unto me, by his permiſſion, be it proſperity or adverſity, ſweet or ſowre, I receive it as from his own hand, with great joy and comfort, and therefore I was never unfortunate; for I never deſired any thing, but the good pleaſure of God: which the poor man having ſaid; The Doctor anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: But what would you ſay (my friend) if God would damn you? If God would damn me (ſaid the poor man) verily if he would uſe me ſo hardly, I have two Arms to embrace him: The one whereof is a profound humility; by the which I am united unto his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly humanity: The other is love and charity, which joyneth men unto his Divinity, by which I would embrace him in ſuch ſort, that he ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to deſcend with me into Hell: And I had rather, without compariſon, be in Hell with God, then to be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him in Paradiſe.</p>
               <p>The Doctor learned in this Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:121281:83"/>That a true reſignation, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companyed with profound Humility of heart, is the ſhorteſt way to attain unto the love of God. After that, he asked of him again, from whence he came; unto whom he made anſwer, that God had ſent him. The Doctor enquired yet of him, Where he had found God? I found him (quoth he) ſo ſoon as I had renounced and forſaken all creatures. And where didſt thou leave him, replyed the Doctor? I left him (anſwered the Beggar) with the pure and clean hearts, and amongſt men of good will. But who art thou (my friend) ſaid the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine unto him? The poor man made him anſwer, That he was a King: And he asking him where his Kingdom was, it is (quoth he) in my ſoul: For I can ſo well rule and govern my ſenſes, as well outward as inward, that all my affections and paſſions do obey unto <hi>REASON:</hi> which Kingdom is without doubt more excellent, then all the Kingdoms of this world.</p>
               <p>Moreover the aforeſaid Doctor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of him, who it was that had brought him to ſo great perfection?
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:121281:84"/>It was ſilence (anſwered the poor man) and mine high and lofty meditation, and the union which I had with God; I could take no repoſe nor comfort in any creature of the world, by the means whereof I found out my God, who will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort me, world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end: <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laus Deo.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise_of_the_soul">
            <pb n="151" facs="tcp:121281:84"/>
            <head>De Anima.</head>
            <p>The Soul is
<list>
                  <item>1. abſolutely
<list>
                        <item>An intellectual ſubſtance enlightened by God.</item>
                        <item>A bodileſs form, framing and ruling the body and created of nothing.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. By relation
<list>
                        <item>1. To the creatures, a ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude of all things, becauſe it comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all things.</item>
                        <item>2. To God, a form of God, becauſe it is after his likeneſs; a breath of life, becauſe it was brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed into us to give us life.</item>
                        <item>3. To his end a ſpirit or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to felicity.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb n="152" facs="tcp:121281:85"/>
            <p>The Soul was ſuppoſed to be of
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Plato,</hi> number moving it ſelf.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> the motive and form of the body.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> a harmony of elements.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hypocrates,</hi> a ſubtile ſpirit.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rabanus,</hi> light.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Democritus,</hi> a Compoſition of Sunny motes.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Aconomius,</hi> a fire.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Parmenides,</hi> a Compound of fire and earth.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Epicurus,</hi> a mixture of ayr and fire.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Gallenus,</hi> a Blood.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hermogenes,</hi> a water, or humid vapour.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The Soul hath divers names in reſpect of his divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations.</p>
            <p>It is called</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Anima,</hi> as it quickeneth the body.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mens,</hi> as it underſtandeth.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Animus,</hi> as it willeth.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ratio,</hi> as it judgeth.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Spiritus,</hi> as it giveth breath.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Senſus,</hi> as it feeleth.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Memoria,</hi> as it remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Voluntas,</hi> as it conſenteth to the thing willed.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="153" facs="tcp:121281:85"/>
            <p>There is a Soul both</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Vegitable, which giveth growth and being; this ſoul is in all plants.</item>
               <item>2. Senſible, which giveth being and ſenſe; and this with the vegitable al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is in beaſts.</item>
               <item>3. Reaſonable, which giveth being, ſenſe, and reaſon; and this with the vegitable and ſenſible is alſo in man; yet are there not divers ſouls in man, but divers faculties, and one reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Soul.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitable Soul hath power to</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Beget and make generation for the preſervation of the Kind.</item>
               <item>2. To nouriſh and ſuſtain the Kind produced.</item>
               <item>3. To increaſe and augment the Kind nouriſhed.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The nouriſhing part of the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitable Soul hath power</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Attractive, to draw into it ſelf neceſſary food.</item>
               <item>2. Digeſtive, to diſpoſe and concoct that food.</item>
               <item>3. Retentive, to hold in the ſtrength of that food.</item>
               <item>4. Expulſive, to ſend the ſuperfluity of this food in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Draught.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="154" facs="tcp:121281:86"/>
            <p>The ſenſible Soul hath power</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive to conceive and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend withal, and that either
<list>
                     <item>Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, as the 5. outward Senſes;
<list>
                           <item>Sight.</item>
                           <item>Hearing.</item>
                           <item>Smelling.</item>
                           <item>Taſte.</item>
                           <item>Touch.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, as the inward Senſes;
<list>
                           <item>Common ſenſe.</item>
                           <item>Imagination.</item>
                           <item>Eſtimation.</item>
                           <item>Phantaſie.</item>
                           <item>Memory.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>2. Motive to move the
<list>
                     <item>1. Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite
<list>
                           <item>Concupiſcible to all deſires.</item>
                           <item>Iraſcible to all paſſions, as joy, grief, hope &amp; fear, in this is contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Senſuality.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty
<list>
                           <item>Natural, which from the liver doth ſtir all the humors of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy by the vital, which from the heart doth move the pulſes by the Arteries.</item>
                           <item>Animal, which from the head doth move the members of the body by the nerves and ſinews.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb n="155" facs="tcp:121281:86"/>
            <p>The object of
<list>
                  <item>Sight is Colour, his organ is the Eye.</item>
                  <item>Hearing is Sound, his organ is the Ear.</item>
                  <item>Smell is Odour, his organ is the Noſe.</item>
                  <item>Taſte is Savor, his organ is the Tongue.</item>
                  <item>Touch is every tangible thing, his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan is the whole body.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The common Senſe is the</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Fountain whence all outward ſenſes flow.</item>
               <item>2. End whither all outward ſenſes are directed.</item>
               <item>3. Judg that determineth the object of every outward ſenſe, and it is called the common Senſe, becauſe it is the head and guider of all the outward Senſes alike.</item>
               <item>His place is in the fore-part of the brain, whither the Senſes, in their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations, have recourſe.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Imagination</p>
            <list>
               <item>Doth preſerve thoſe Impreſſions which the common Senſe receiveth.</item>
               <item>Doth defer to the eſtimation thoſe forms reſerved: His place is in the fore part of the brain, whither the the common Senſe tendeth and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volveth his Impreſſions.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="156" facs="tcp:121281:87"/>
            <p>The Eſtimation</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Apprehendeth natural intentions of thoſe Impreſſions.</item>
               <item>2. Determineth what is to be followed and what avoyded. His ſeat is the middle part or Cell of the brain, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Imagination ſtretcheth his Impreſſes.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Phantaſie compareth
<list>
                  <item>Forms with forms, as black with white.</item>
                  <item>Forms with Intenſions, as the form of a wolf with the flight of a wolf.</item>
                  <item>Intention with Intention, as the feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of her own with the rejecting of another.</item>
                  <item>His ſeat is betwixt the Memory and the Eſtimation, becauſe is concerns them both; for it is enlightened by Eſtimation &amp; maintained by Memory.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Led by Phantaſie, Creatures</p>
            <list>
               <item>Make them caves and neſts.</item>
               <item>Provide them ſuſtenance a far off.</item>
               <item>Know and diſtinguiſh this to be this.</item>
               <item>Chooſe and refuſe this and that.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="157" facs="tcp:121281:87"/>
            <p>Memory</p>
            <list>
               <item>Doth receive the operations of all the Senſes from the Common Senſe.</item>
               <item>Doth reſerve the things receive, as Imagination doth the Intents: His ſeat is in the hinder part of the head.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Memory is</p>
            <list>
               <item>Artificial, got by litteral obſervation and practiſe.</item>
               <item>Natural, inſtilled in our compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Soul hath</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Inbred Powers.</item>
               <item>2. Acquired Habits.</item>
               <item>3. Inferred Paſſions.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The inbred powers of the Soul are</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<list>
                     <item>Speculative, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template withall.</item>
                     <item>Practick, to exerciſe; and this is the Cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative part of the Soul which appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth withall.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>2. Will
<list>
                     <item>Natural, which is directed by inſtinct.</item>
                     <item>Deliberative, which is guided by reaſon; and this is the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive part of the ſoul which produceth all the operations both of body and mind.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb n="158" facs="tcp:121281:88"/>
            <p>The Soul
<list>
                  <item>Knoweth the good, by the ſpeculative underſtanding.</item>
                  <item>Affecteth the good, by practick under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</item>
                  <item>Diſcerneth good and evil, by Reaſon.</item>
                  <item>Chooſeth the good from evil, by free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will.</item>
                  <item>Conſenteth to choſen good, by recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied will.</item>
                  <item>Inventeth means to accompliſh it by will.</item>
                  <item>Raiſeth it ſelf to vertue by the motive of the Conſcience.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>This is the order and degree of Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding;</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Senſe perceiveth.</item>
               <item>2. Imagination repreſenteth.</item>
               <item>3. Underſtanding formeth.</item>
               <item>4. Wit deviſeth.</item>
               <item>5. Reaſon judgeth.</item>
               <item>6. Memory preſerveth.</item>
               <item>7. Intelligence apprehendeth.</item>
               <item>8. Contemplation perfecteth,</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Soul knoweth things</p>
            <list>
               <item>Preſent, by Senſe.</item>
               <item>Abſent and to come, by Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</item>
               <item>Abſent and paſt, by Memory.</item>
               <item>It ſelf, by reflection upon it ſelf.</item>
               <item>God, by elevation above it ſelf.</item>
               <item>Creatures, by humiliation of it ſelf.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="159" facs="tcp:121281:88"/>
            <p>The Soul is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Becauſe it is capable of felicity, which is eternal.</item>
               <item>2. Becauſe it is made after Gods ſimilitude, which is immortal.</item>
               <item>3. Becauſe it hath no contrariety to corrupt it.</item>
            </list>
            <p>A Spirit doth u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite the Soul un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, whoſe</p>
            <list>
               <item>Fleſh &amp; bones are made of earth.</item>
               <item>Humors (to wit) Blood, Phlegm, Choller, and Melancollick, are made of water.</item>
               <item>Lights are made of ayr to cool the heat of the heart.</item>
               <item>Heart containeth fire to temper the moiſture of the brain.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the body are</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Radical, wherein is the root of life, as in the
<list>
                     <item>Liver.</item>
                     <item>Heart.</item>
                     <item>Brain.</item>
                     <item>Teſts.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>2. Serviceable, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey the natural, ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal and vital ſpirits, as the
<list>
                     <item>Veines.</item>
                     <item>Nerves.</item>
                     <item>Arteries</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>3. Official, to perform the offices of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as the
<list>
                     <item>Eyes.</item>
                     <item>Hands.</item>
                     <item>Feet.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb n="160" facs="tcp:121281:89"/>
            <p>The Soul was uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the body</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. To teach us the union of our Soul and God.</item>
               <item>2. To accompliſh and perfect the work of God. For as God made one creature meerly ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, as the Angels; and one meerly corporal, as the World; ſo he hath made one both ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual &amp; corporal, which is Man.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The acquired habits of the Soul be</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Vertues.</item>
               <item>2. Habitual Cuſtoms got by induſtry and uſe.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Vertues proceed from grace</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Incoative, which begetteth them.</item>
               <item>2. Continuing, which maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them.</item>
               <item>3. Perfecting, which conſummates and acteth them.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Vertue in reſpect of the</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Giver, is the operation of God in man.</item>
               <item>2. Subject, is the habitation of a well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>governed mind.</item>
               <item>3. Working, is a habit bringing us to Mediocrity.</item>
               <item>4. End, is a diſpoſition to the beſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</item>
               <item>5. Quality, a good faculty whereby we live well.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="161" facs="tcp:121281:89"/>
            <p>All Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Underſtanding hard matters</item>
               <item>2. Enduring adverſe croſſes.</item>
               <item>3. Abſtaining from pleaſures.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Vertue is placed in Doing</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Doing neither
<list>
                     <item>above Meaſure</item>
                     <item>nor under Meaſure</item>
                     <item>but in Meaſure.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>2. Having neither
<list>
                     <item>Exceſs </item>
                     <item>nor Defect.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>3 Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<list>
                     <item>Proſperity with hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blenes</item>
                     <item>Adverſity with patience,</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The tree of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue hath his</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Seed, Fear.</item>
               <item>2. Irigation, Grace.</item>
               <item>3. Root, Faith.</item>
               <item>4. Bud, Devotion.</item>
               <item>5. Growth, Deſire.</item>
               <item>6. Strength, Charity.</item>
               <item>7. Greenneſs, Hope.</item>
               <item>8. Leaf, Heed.</item>
               <item>9. Flouriſh, Diſcipline.</item>
               <item>10. Fruit, Doctrine.</item>
               <item>11. Maturity, Patience.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of Vertue is to</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Remove tentations, this ſetles Vertue in the Root.</item>
               <item>2. Multiply vertuous actions, this is the flower of Vertue.</item>
               <item>3. Delight in goodneſs, this the fruit of Vertue.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="162" facs="tcp:121281:90"/>
            <p>There be four mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Faith to conceive them.</item>
               <item>2. Charity to bring them forth.</item>
               <item>3. Wiſdom to diſpoſe and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them.</item>
               <item>4. Humility to ſuſtain and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold them.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Men are more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinable to one vertue then to another</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Becauſe they have the gift of that ſpecial vertue.</item>
               <item>2. Becauſe their complexion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clineth to that vertue.</item>
               <item>3. Becauſe uſe exerciſeth them in that vertue.</item>
               <item>4. Becauſe that vertue is not ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by his contrary vice.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Vertues are</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing to God
<list>
                     <item>1. Wiſdom, which ruleth our affections and will.</item>
                     <item>2. Intelligence, which gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth cogitations and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings.</item>
                     <item>3. Knowledg of the Spirit, which governeth both the will and underſtanding.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>2. Conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinal to converſe with men, as
<list>
                     <item>1. Honeſty, to order our private actions.</item>
                     <item>2. Liberality, to benefit our neighbours.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb n="163" facs="tcp:121281:90"/>
            <p>Conſuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues are,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Moral to inform our manners.</item>
               <item>2. Oeconomical to diſpoſe our family.</item>
               <item>3. Political to order Kingdoms and Cities.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Mans life is guided by ſeven Vertues; By</p>
            <list>
               <item>3 Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logical:
<list>
                     <item>1. Faith, whereby we know God as Veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</item>
                     <item>2. Hope, whereby we truſt in God as in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity.</item>
                     <item>3. Charity, wherby we love God as the only Bonity.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>4 Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal:
<list>
                     <item>4. Prudence, which rectifieth Reaſon.</item>
                     <item>5. Fortitude, which tempereth Anger.</item>
                     <item>6. Temperance, which moderates deſire.</item>
                     <item>7. Juſtice, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth all our pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb n="164" facs="tcp:121281:91"/>
            <p n="1">1. Faith is either</p>
            <list>
               <item>Hiſtorical, to believe the hiſtories of Scripture.</item>
               <item>Miraculous, to believe in Chriſt for Miracles.</item>
               <item>Diabolical, to confeſs of neceſſity without Hope.</item>
               <item>Juſtifying, to believe and confeſs with full Hope.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="2">2. Hope is either for</p>
            <list>
               <item>Pardon</item>
               <item>Grace.</item>
               <item>Glory.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="3">3. Charity is refered</p>
            <list>
               <item>Naturally to our ſelf, this is called Love,</item>
               <item>To our Parents, this is called Piety.</item>
               <item>To our Neighbours, this is called Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection.</item>
               <item>To our follows, which is called Friendſhip, and contains
<list>
                     <item>1. Familiarity.</item>
                     <item>2. Society.</item>
                     <item>3. Benevolence.</item>
                     <item>4. Benignity.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>To our Enemies, which is called
<list>
                     <item>Exitation.</item>
                     <item>Love of Innocency.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>To God, which is properly called
<list>
                     <item>Charity.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="4">4. Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Loveth all things by the line of Reaſon.</item>
               <item>2. Neither willeth nor doth any thing, otherwiſe then right.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="165" facs="tcp:121281:91"/>
            <p>Prudence muſt be in the</p>
            <list>
               <item>Heart, to guide our thoughts and intents.</item>
               <item>Mouth, to order our ſpeech.</item>
               <item>Works, to grace our actions.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Prudence may be divided into</p>
            <list>
               <item>Intelligence, to underſtand things preſent.</item>
               <item>Prudence, to gueſs at things to come.</item>
               <item>Remembrance, to recal matters paſt.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="5">5. Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Brings the appetite under the Rule of Reaſon.</item>
               <item>2. Never exceedeth the Laws of Moderation.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance may be divided into</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Continency, which refrain and reſtrain pleaſures.</item>
               <item>2. Charity,</item>
               <item>3. Clemency, which appeaſeth anger</item>
               <item>4. Sobriety, which avoydeth exceſs in Eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</item>
               <item>5. Modeſty, which eſcheweth vain-gloriouſneſs in our words or actions.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="6">6 For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Attempteth dangers diſcreetly, not raſhly.</item>
               <item>2. Endureth calamity, not weakly but patiently.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="166" facs="tcp:121281:92"/>
            <p>Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude may be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Magnificence, which deviſeth and atchieveth brave exploits.</item>
               <item>2. Confidence, which is not daunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with appearance of peril.</item>
               <item>3. Patience, which willingly ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth miſ-fortune for vertue or profit.</item>
               <item>4. Perſeverance, which continueth in doing and ſuffering valiantly.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="7">7. Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Giveth every one his due.</item>
               <item>2. Is not deflected or wrung from Truth, by
<list>
                     <item>Love.</item>
                     <item>Fear.</item>
                     <item>Rancor.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Juſtice may be divided into</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Religion, which bindeth to give due to God.</item>
               <item>2. Piety, which tyeth us to give duty to our parents and kindred.</item>
               <item>3. Favor, whereby we return due to our friend.</item>
               <item>4. Vindication, whereby we vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate our ſelves from injuries.</item>
               <item>5. Obſervance, whereby we give due to our betters.</item>
               <item>6. Verity, whereby we deal uprightly in the eye of men.</item>
               <item>7. Equity, whereby we deal juſtly in our conſcience, if the matter be not manifeſt to the world.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="theological_definitions">
            <pb n="167" facs="tcp:121281:92"/>
            <head>Definitions Theological.</head>
            <p>ALL Divinity is ſaid to be put into a circle, becauſe one attribute is affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of another, and for God, to have a thing is to be that thing, his having is his being, his moving is his ſtanding, his running is his reſting.</p>
            <p>He is the abſolute Reaſon in which all Alterity is Unity, all Diverſity, Identity.</p>
            <p>The Inviſibility of God is repreſented by contracted ſhadows, conceived in the mind and underſtanding, and in the things that are; It ſelf being free from all contraction, as not being ſubject to quantity nor quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, time nor place, but is the abſolute Form of all forms, the adequate meaſure of all things, and ſuperexalted, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>He therefore that ſees God, ſees nothing diverſe from himſelf, becauſe he ſees his own truth, or the truth of himſelf.</p>
            <p>God is ſeen alike by all that ſee him.</p>
            <p>God is the proper object of the mind.</p>
            <p>When man attributeh a face to God, he ſeeks not for it out of the Latitude of the
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:121281:93"/>Species of man, becauſe his judgment is contracted; <hi>ergo,</hi> excedes not the paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Contraction, as if a Lion ſhould aſcribe him a face, he would give only a lions face, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>All things that ſee his face are not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to admire it which cannot be ſeen until a man enter into a ſecret and hidden ſilence, where there is neither knowledg nor conception of a face; For this Miſt, Cloud, Darkneſs and Ignorance he enters into when he ſurmounts all know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg.</p>
            <p>He that ſees Gods Face, ſees all things openly, and there is nothing hid unto him; yea, he knows and hath all things, becauſe no man ſees God but he that hath Him</p>
            <p>No man comes to God, becauſe unap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachable.</p>
            <p>No man can take God, except he give himſelf unto him.</p>
            <p>How wilt thou give thy ſelf unto me, unleſs thou giveſt all things that are.</p>
            <p>How wilt thou give thy ſelf unto me, unleſs thou give my ſelf unto me; whileſt I reſt in this ſilence of contemplation, and
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:121281:93"/>hearken unto the Word of God, which cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not to ſpeak within me, I ſhall be freed from the ſervice of ſin, and enjoy God as his own gift and the infinite treaſure of all deſirable things.</p>
            <p>God ſees all things, and every particular, together or at once.</p>
            <p>God ſtandeth ſtill, and is moved together, becauſe neither motion nor reſt without God.</p>
            <p>Thou, O God, art wholy preſent to each thing at once, and yet art thou nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther moved nor reſteſt, becauſe ſuper-ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aited and free from all.</p>
            <p>God is above all ſtation or motion, in moſt ſimple and abſolute Infinity.</p>
            <p>Gods eternal Word cannot be mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, nor diverſe, nor variable, nor change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, becauſe it is ſimple Eternity; No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can there be paſt or to come, where to come and paſt concide with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
            <p>In God the End concides with the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning. <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega</hi> are the ſame.</p>
            <p>All things are all that they are, becauſe God is.</p>
            <pb n="170" facs="tcp:121281:94"/>
            <p>God is no ſuch thing as can be ſaid, or conceived, but infinitely and abſolutely ſuperexalted above all things.</p>
            <p>To underſtand Infinity is to comprehend that which is incomprehenſible.</p>
            <p>The underſtanding knows it ſelf ignorant of God, becauſe it knows he cannot be known, unleſs that which is unknowable be known, the inviſible be ſeen, the inac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſible be approached, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>God is an end without an end, becauſe the end of himſelf; his end is his eſſence; <hi>ergo,</hi> that end, which is the end or bound of itſelf, is infinite; <hi>ergo,</hi> God is the bound without bound, which paſſeth all reaſon, for it infolds contradiction, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Contradiction in Infinity, is without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, becauſe Infinity.</p>
            <p>In Infinity, is oppoſition of oppoſites without oppoſition.</p>
            <p>If there were Infinity and ſomething be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides it, it were not Infinity.</p>
            <p>Infinity complicates all things, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be beſides it, or diverſe unto it.</p>
            <p>Infinity is ſo all things, that it is none of them all.</p>
            <p>Infinity is neither great, nor little, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing that can be named, neither great
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:121281:94"/>nor leſs, nor equall to any thing.</p>
            <p>Neither yet is it equality, as contracted equality is underſtood, but it is infinite e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality, not capable of more nor leſs.</p>
            <div type="theological_and_philosophical_definitions">
               <head>Definitions Theological and Philoſophical.</head>
               <p>GOd is the Father, and the good; In Being all things: For he both will be this and is it; and yet all this for himſelf.</p>
               <p>But then ſhal we ſee the chief good when we have nothing at all to ſay of it. <hi>[Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis holy Ser.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the knowledg of it is a divine ſilence, and the Reſt of all the Senſes; For neither can he that underſtands that, underſtand; nor he that ſees that, ſee, nor hear any other thing; nor, in ſum, move, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>For it is poſſible for the ſoul to be Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, while it lodgeth in the body, contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plating the beauty of the Good.</p>
               <p>God, and the Father, and Good, is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpoken, nor heard: and Knowledg differs from Senſe.</p>
               <p>Knowledg is the gift of God: All know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg is unbodily uſing the mind as an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as the mind uſeth the body.</p>
               <pb n="172" facs="tcp:121281:95"/>
               <p>That which is good, is immaterial and not paſſable; as the world is the firſt of all paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble things, and the ſecond of the things that are, was once made, is ever in generation, of things that have quantity and quality, <hi>ergo,</hi> not that good. The world is a ſphere, <hi>i. e.</hi> a head, above the head nothing mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial, beneath the feet nothing intelectual.</p>
               <p>All things depend of one beginning, and the beginning depends of that which is one and alone.</p>
               <p>The beginning is moved, and that which is one ſtandeth and abideth unmoved.</p>
               <p>God is above all, and the Beams of God are operations.</p>
               <p>If God were apparent, he were not all; for whatſoever is apparent is generated; but God is always, and makes all other things manifeſt, and aparent is nothing but generation.</p>
               <p>God which maketh all things appear, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in all and by all, eſpecially in thoſe things wherein himſelf liſteth.</p>
               <p>The underſtanding ſees that which is not manifeſt, it ſelf being not manifeſt, yea, it contemplates the Image of God.</p>
               <p>The things that are he hath made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, and the things that are not he hath hid in himſelf.</p>
               <pb n="173" facs="tcp:121281:95"/>
               <p>This is God that is better then any name, that is ſecret, that is moſt manifeſt, ſeen by the mind; that hath no body, that hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bodies: rather there is nothing of any body, which is not he; for he alone is all things.</p>
               <p>Which way ſhall I look when I praiſe thee, upward downward, outward, inward? All things are in thee, from thee, thou giveſt all things, haſt all things, and there is nothing that thou haſt not.</p>
               <p>Thou art what I am, what I do or ſay, thou art all things, and there is nothing that thou art not.</p>
               <p>Good is in nothing but in God alone, or rather God himſelf is that good always.</p>
               <p>One is the beginning of all things, for it giveth all things.</p>
               <p>God wanteth nothing, that he ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire it, nor can any thing be taken from him; the loſs whereof may grieve him.</p>
               <p>Nothing is ſtronger then he, that he ſhould be oppoſed by it, nor equal to him, that he ſhould be in love with it; ſo that nothing remains in his eſſence, but only the good.</p>
               <p>The good is only in that which is not ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated. God is the fulneſs of good, or
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:121281:96"/>good the fulneſs of God. Beauty in God is above compariſon; and that good is inimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, as God himſelf.</p>
               <p>Every motion is in ſtation, and is moved of ſtation. There is nothing empty; only that which is not, is empfy and a ſtranger to exiſtence.</p>
               <p>That which is, could not be, if it were not full of exiſtence: that which is in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence, can never be made empty.</p>
               <p>God is nothing that can be named, but the cauſe of all things.</p>
               <p>God is to be worſhipped by theſe two appellations, Good, (for God is good, not according to honor, but nature,) and Father, becauſe of his making of all things,</p>
               <p>Nothing can be like the unlike, and only One; neither hath he given of his power to any other,</p>
               <p>Whatſoever is in the world, is moved ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther according to augmentation or diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Generation is not a Creation of life, but a production of things to ſenſe: Neither is change death, but occultation or hiding of that which was.</p>
               <p>God is both act and power, and there is nothing that is not God.</p>
               <pb n="175" facs="tcp:121281:96"/>
               <p>Things that appear not are hard to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved. Things moſt apparent, are evil; but the good is ſecret, having neither form nor figure; it is like unto it ſelf, but unlike all other things.</p>
               <p>Unity is the original of all things, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Root and Beginning.</p>
               <p>Nothing is without beginning, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning is of nothing but it ſelf, for it is the beginning of all other things.</p>
               <p>Unity therefore, being the beginning, containeth every number, it ſelf being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained of none; it begetteth every number, it ſelf being begotten of none other num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</p>
               <p>Every thing that is begotten or made, is imperfect, may be divided, increaſed, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhed.</p>
               <p>To the perfect there happeneth none of theſe.</p>
               <p>That which is increaſed is increaſed by Unity.</p>
               <p>Truth is the moſt perfect vertue, higheſt, not troubled by matter, not encompaſſed by a body; naked, clear, unchangeable, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable, unalterable, good.</p>
               <p>Every thing that is altered, is a lye; for being changed it ſhews other appearances.</p>
               <pb n="176" facs="tcp:121281:97"/>
               <p>Man, as man, is not true; for that which is true, hath of it ſelf alone it conſtitution, remains and abides to it ſelf according as it is.</p>
               <p>But Man doth not abide of himſelf, but is turned and changed, age after age, and Idea after Idea; and this while he is yet in the Tabernacle: and being in many appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances and changes, is falſhood.</p>
               <p>Nothing that remans not in it ſelf is true.</p>
               <p>The firſt Truth, the one and only, not of matter, not in a body, without colour, without figure, immutable, unalterable, and always is.</p>
               <p>But Falſhood is corrupted.</p>
               <p>Corruption followeth every generation that it may again be generated.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:121281:97"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>WHat is perfect, and what is imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. <hi>pag. 1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What is ſin. <hi>pag. 4</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The ſin of <hi>Adam. pag. 6</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That all good is only God. <hi>pag. 7</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the putting off the old man. <hi>pag. 8</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How the life of man is to be compoſed. <hi>pag. 10</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the two eyes of Chriſt. <hi>pag. 11</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Whether in this life eternal happineſs may be taſted. <hi>pag. 13</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Except goodneſs be in man, it cannot make man happy. <hi>pag. 15</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the deſire of thoſe who be illuminated. <hi>pag. 17</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Hell and of the Kingdom of Heaven. <hi>pag. 19</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of true peace and happineſs. <hi>pag. 23</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> and the amendment made by Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>pag. 24</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What the old and new Man is. <hi>pag. 27</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That a man ought to attribute all good to God, and evil to himſelf. <hi>pag. 32</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That a Chriſtian life is the beſt. <hi>pag. 33</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:121281:98"/>
               <item>Of the way to Chriſt. <hi>pag. 35</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the life of Chriſt is envyed of humane wiſdom. <hi>pag. 36</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The eſtate of a Chriſtian is not to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed. <hi>pag. 37</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the world is mad. <hi>pag. 39</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the way unto the life of Chriſt. <hi>pag. 42</hi>
               </item>
               <item>In what man true Chriſt is. <hi>pag. 43</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What it is to be rich in Spirit. <hi>pag. 45</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What it is to be poor in Spirit. <hi>pag. 48</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That all things are to be left and loſt. <hi>pag. 54</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the inward man is immoveably joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with God, the outward man notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding is moved. <hi>pag. 55</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That no man in this life can be free from pain. <hi>pag. 57</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That to a juſt man no Law is to be given. <hi>pag. 59</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of true and falſe Lights, alſo of perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in the life of Chriſt. <hi>pag. 61</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That God is one and ſimple good, and only to be loved. <hi>pag. 63</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That a deified man knoweth nothing but love. <hi>pag. 67</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the will of man is prone to evil, and therefore to be forſaken. <hi>pag. 69</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of true humility and ſpiritual powerty. <hi>pag. 71</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:121281:98"/>
               <item>That ſin only is contrary to God. <hi>pag. 73</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That God in himſelf is impatiable, in man he is patiable. <hi>pag. 75</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the life of Chriſt is to be loved for it ſelf, not for reward. <hi>pag. 77</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That God is above all order. <hi>pag. 79</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The deſcription of the falſe Light. <hi>pag. 83</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Who and what a deified man is. <hi>pag. 92</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Whether God may be known and yet no loved. <hi>pag. 95</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the true love of God. <hi>pag. 100</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That there is nothing contrary to God but mans own will. <hi>pag. 106</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Where the life of Chriſt is, there is Chriſt. <hi>pag. 109</hi>
               </item>
               <item>☞ To be content with God. <hi>pag. 111</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Whether ſin is to be loved. <hi>pag. 113</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That Faith bringeth forth Knowledg. <hi>pag. 115</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of mans own proper Will. <hi>pag. 116</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Why God created mans own will, ſeeing it is contrary to the eternal will. <hi>pag. 118</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Why God created the will. <hi>pag. 120</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How the Devil and <hi>Adam</hi> challenge will to themſelves. <hi>pag. 122</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That in what man the truth is, in that man free will is alſo. <hi>pag. 124</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Treating of Chriſt and his Croſs. <hi>pag. 127</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the Imitation of Chriſt. <hi>pag. 129</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:121281:99"/>
               <item>How the Father draweth to the Son, and the Son reciprocally to the Father. <hi>pag. 131</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How God becometh all things in man. <hi>pag. 133</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That God alone is to be loved and honored. <hi>pag. 135</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Certain grave ſayings, by which the ſcholar of Chriſt may ſearch into himſelf, and know what is to be ſought and ſtrived for concerning the true inward uniting of himſelf to the one ſupream good. <hi>pag. 138</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to put on God by a moſt perfect way. <hi>pag. 144</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Perfection in the firſt, ſecond, third and fourth degree. <hi>pag. 145</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Communication of Dr <hi>Thaulerus</hi> with a Beggar, wherein is contained the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of a perfect man. <hi>pag. 146</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An exact Treatiſe of the Definitions of the Soul. <hi>pag. 151</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Definitions Theological and Philoſophical. <hi>pag. 167</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
